<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hebdomada sacra: A weekes deuotion: or, Seuen poeticall meditations vpon the second chapter of St. Matthewes gospell. Written, by Roger Cocks.</title>
            <author>Cocks, Roger, fl. 1630-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118643</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853850</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853850</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19248</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19248)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1062:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hebdomada sacra: A weekes deuotion: or, Seuen poeticall meditations vpon the second chapter of St. Matthewes gospell. Written, by Roger Cocks.</title>
                  <author>Cocks, Roger, fl. 1630-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 74 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston for Henrt Seile, and are to be sold at his shop in St. Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Tygers head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A weekes deuotion.</note>
                  <note>First leaf blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Meditationse --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19248:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19248:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19248:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19248:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19248:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19248:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Hebdomada Sacra: A WEEKES DEVOTION: OR, SEVEN POETI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALL MEDITATIONS, VPON THE SECOND Chapter of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Matthewes Goſpell. Written, by ROGER COCKS.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Woodcut printer's device, featuring a bearded face (not in McKerrow).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Imprinted by Felix Kyngston for Henry Seile, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pauls Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Tygers head. 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19248:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19248:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, IAMES, LORD <hi>Strange.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>POetry (noble Lord) in theſe looſe times,</l>
               <l>Wherin men rather loue, then loath their crimes,</l>
               <l>If hand in hand with piety ſhe goe,</l>
               <l>(Though without bluſhing ſhe her face may ſhow)</l>
               <l>Finds but cold welcome, ſuch things onely take,</l>
               <l>As flatter greatneſſe, or fond fancie make</l>
               <l>A baud to baſe delight: yet grauer eyes</l>
               <l>No ſacred lines (though rudely drawne) deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>And ſuch are yours: vpon this worke of mine</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe to let them fall, or rather ſhine,</l>
               <l>With kind acceptance doe but daine to grace it,</l>
               <l>And enuie ſhall want power to deface it.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19248:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>REader my fortunes are ſo meanely friended,</l>
               <l>I come into thy preſence vncommended:</l>
               <l>Nor would I haue thee for <hi>Encomiums</hi> looke,</l>
               <l>Or frontiſpeece, farre better then the booke,</l>
               <l>My veine is not ſo high, to be commended,</l>
               <l>Nor yet ſo low, but it may be defended,</l>
               <l>By one ſole Patron: Some that carpe will gather,</l>
               <l>This is no Poem, but a Sermon rather,</l>
               <l>But let them know who thus ſeuerely note it,</l>
               <l>No profeſt Poet, but a Preacher wrote it.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="meditative_poems">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19248:5"/>
            <head>A WEEKES DEVOTION.</head>
            <div n="Sunday" type="daily_meditation">
               <head>Sundaies Meditation, or the firſt <hi>Canto</hi> for the firſt day.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Christs obſcure Birth deſcrib'd, the Place,</l>
                     <l>To which he did vouchſafe ſuch Grace.</l>
                     <l>The Time when he was borne is nam'd:</l>
                     <l>The Iew for vnbeliefe is blam'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Caeſar</hi> famous for his Gallian warre,</l>
                  <l>Had ended that vnnaturall ciuill jarre,</l>
                  <l>Twixt him and <hi>Pompey,</hi> and by his defeat,</l>
                  <l>Got him a greater name the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that of great,</l>
                  <l>Perpetuall Dictator, Enuie roſe</l>
                  <l>To ioyne with coward Murder, and depoſe</l>
                  <l>Vertue from bearing rule, the Senate made</l>
                  <l>A bloudy ſhambles, and a couert ſhade.</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19248:6"/>
                  <l>For horrid treaſon, was the fatall place,</l>
                  <l>Where his blacke tragedie was wrought, in baſe</l>
                  <l>Vnmanly manner, falling by the hand,</l>
                  <l>Of an vnthankefull <hi>Brutus:</hi> the command,</l>
                  <l>Of Romes faire Empire then in three did lie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Augustus, Lepidus,</hi> and <hi>Anthonie:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lepidus</hi> ſoone gaue o're, whether in doubt,</l>
                  <l>Had he held ſtill, he could not long hold out,</l>
                  <l>Or for ſome other reaſon, t'other twaine,</l>
                  <l>Shar'd equally Romes glorie, and the gaine</l>
                  <l>Of forraine kingdomes, till at length there paſt,</l>
                  <l>(For great mens freindſhip doth not alwaies laſt)</l>
                  <l>Vnkindneſſe twixt them, <hi>Anthonie</hi> had wed</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Siſter, but forſooke her bed,</l>
                  <l>For Aegypts <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> This gaue fire</l>
                  <l>To new diſſention, his vniuſt deſire</l>
                  <l>Muſt be made good by Armes, for gentle words</l>
                  <l>Turne him to furie, our impartiall Swords</l>
                  <l>Shall ſoone decide this difference ſaid he,</l>
                  <l>And ſoone they did indeed, fate did agree</l>
                  <l>To ſecond his proud ſaying, for his forces,</l>
                  <l>Broke by <hi>Augustus</hi> powers, he life diuorces,</l>
                  <l>From her weake hold, and being thus o'recome,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caeſar</hi> went backe triumphant vnto Rome.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Augustus</hi> now hauing ſole rule, ſoone brought</l>
                  <l>His Prouinces in awe, all humblie ſought</l>
                  <l>To haue his friendſhip, ſome few<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> did rebell,</l>
                  <l>But with vndaunted courage he did quell</l>
                  <l>Their vaine attempts, and to his fames encreaſe,</l>
                  <l>Eſtabliſht through the world a welcome peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>While <hi>Ianus</hi> Temple was ſhut vp and warre,</l>
                  <l>Chas'd backe to <hi>Plutoes</hi> kingdome, while no iarre</l>
                  <l>Kept out ſoule-ioyning concord, whoſe ſweete art</l>
                  <l>Did Speares to Mattockes, Swords to Plowes conuert,</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19248:6"/>
                  <l>While <hi>Noahs</hi> Doue brought in her mouth (the Marke</l>
                  <l>Of generall peace) and Oliue Branch toth' Arke,</l>
                  <l>Chriſt the celeſtiall <hi>Salomon</hi> was borne,</l>
                  <l>That King of peace, whoſe <hi>Amalthaean</hi> horne,</l>
                  <l>Powr'd peace and plenty on vs; ſo they ſay,</l>
                  <l>That when the Eagle flies abroad to prey,</l>
                  <l>The pratling birds are ſilent, ſhould not then</l>
                  <l>Warres tongue be ſilent, when the beſt of men</l>
                  <l>Like to a Royall Eagle from his neſt,</l>
                  <l>Came from the Virgins wombe in manhood dreſt.</l>
                  <l>When Halcyons build their neſt, &amp; breed their yong,</l>
                  <l>The Seas are quiet, the winde findes no tongue,</l>
                  <l>'Twas fit the world ſhould haue the like behauiour,</l>
                  <l>When the pure Virgin did bring forth our Sauiour.</l>
                  <l>Philoſophers obſerue the dewes deſcent,</l>
                  <l>Is in a cleare night, when the winde is pent<note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>In Aeols priſon: and the Prophet told</l>
                  <l>Chriſt ſhould come downe like dew, and ſuch, behold,</l>
                  <l>Was his ſweet entrance, neuer was the earth</l>
                  <l>So much refreſht by dew, as by his birth,</l>
                  <l>Fit was it then for warres loud noiſe to ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>That this dew might come in a calme of peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If in two Kingdomes, ſuppoſe <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which long in hoſtile manner did aduance.</l>
                  <l>Armes againſt armes, one Kings eldeſt ſonne</l>
                  <l>Marries the others daughter, warres are done,</l>
                  <l>And they which earſt contended eagerly,</l>
                  <l>Now meet in loue, and feaſt in royalty,</l>
                  <l>So ſtood the caſe with vs, by faire pretence,</l>
                  <l>Malicious Satan made man to commence</l>
                  <l>A warre with God, a warre that would haue wrought</l>
                  <l>His endleſſe ruine, had not mercie ſought</l>
                  <l>A meanes to ſettle peace, the onely ſon</l>
                  <l>Of the Almightie, when he did put on</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19248:7"/>
                  <l>That veile of fleſh, did by it faſt combine</l>
                  <l>Our humane nature to his owne diuine,</l>
                  <l>And made a reconcilement, which no power</l>
                  <l>Can breake or time weare out, though euery houre</l>
                  <l>Satan attempt new practiſes, and Hell</l>
                  <l>Spit out her rankeſt venome, to expell</l>
                  <l>Man from his Makers fauour, but her ſpite</l>
                  <l>Falls on her head redoubled, while delight</l>
                  <l>Crownes our deſires, ſuch happy vnion gan</l>
                  <l>The bleſt Meſſias make 'twixt God and man.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No ſooner had <hi>Augustus</hi> brought each land<note place="margin">Luke 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Into ſubiection, but by his command</l>
                  <l>A generall Taxe was laid on euery nation,</l>
                  <l>Iudea 'mongſt the reſt, by Proclamation,</l>
                  <l>Each perſon to his natiue city went</l>
                  <l>There to be taxed: O that men were bent</l>
                  <l>With ready minde, and prompt alacrity,</l>
                  <l>To yeeld obedience vnto Gods decree,</l>
                  <l>As well as <hi>Caeſars,</hi> in the ranke of thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who with ſubmiſſiue dutie did diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>Their wills to this edict, a bleſſed paire:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the iuſt, <hi>Mary</hi> the chaſt and faire,</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Abrahams</hi> iſſue, both of <hi>Dauids</hi> ſtemme,</l>
                  <l>Came vnto <hi>Dauids</hi> City, <hi>Bethlehem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There to be taxed, as the Law requir'd,</l>
                  <l>She being neere her time, which ſoone expir'd,</l>
                  <l>While they were there the dayes accompliſhed,</l>
                  <l>That the pure Virgin ſhould be brought to bed,</l>
                  <l>And yet that phraſe ist but improper heere,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe the Inne, though full of gueſts, yet cleare,</l>
                  <l>Of Grace and goodneſſe, would afford no roome,</l>
                  <l>Where ſhe might child her iſſue, her ripe wombe,</l>
                  <l>Found, ſaue a ſtable, no conuenient place,</l>
                  <l>To reſt it ſelfe, hard hearts whom ſuch a caſe,</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19248:7"/>
                  <l>Mou'd to no pitty, heere ſhe forth did bring</l>
                  <l>The Worlds Redeemer, heauens eternall King.</l>
                  <l>A King, where were the nobles of his Court?</l>
                  <l>Where all his followers? Where the full reſort</l>
                  <l>Of honourable Matrons? to attend</l>
                  <l>Vpon his mother, was there neere a Friend</l>
                  <l>To giue ſoft muſique? by whoſe gentle touch</l>
                  <l>Her ſorrowes might be ſwagde, did all hearts grutch</l>
                  <l>To lend aſſiſtance? at a Princes birth</l>
                  <l>The voice of ioy ſpeakes high, and from the earth,</l>
                  <l>Vnnumbred fires to ſuch perfection grow,</l>
                  <l>As they would make another heauen below,</l>
                  <l>Heere all was huſht and ſilent, to his owne</l>
                  <l>Chriſt came vnentertaind, becauſe vnknowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But why, O Lord, wert thou thus poorely borne?</l>
                  <l>Why didſt thou make thy ſelfe to be a ſcorne</l>
                  <l>To after Ages? Was it to conceale</l>
                  <l>Thy Deity from Satan? or reueale</l>
                  <l>Thy vnexampled goodneſſe vnto man?</l>
                  <l>The like whereof, ſince time and place began</l>
                  <l>To circumſcribe our actions, was not knowne,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall vnto ſucceeding age be ſhowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As Iſraels King did once his habite change,<note place="margin">1. King. 22.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When he wagde warre 'gainſt Syria and did range</l>
                  <l>The field in ſtrange diſguiſe: So Chriſt our King</l>
                  <l>Whom an vnbounded loue from heauen did bring,</l>
                  <l>To fight gainſt helliſh Syrians, and by armes</l>
                  <l>To giue vs freedome from death-threatning harmes,</l>
                  <l>Exchang'd his habite for bright Maieſtie,</l>
                  <l>Clothing himſelfe with baſe infirmity:</l>
                  <l>If ſome great King put on his royall Crowne,</l>
                  <l>And regall ornaments, he may be knowne,</l>
                  <l>But if his Kingly dignity he hide</l>
                  <l>In vile aray, he may paſſe vndiſcried.</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19248:8"/>
                  <l>So had our kingly Sauiour cloth'd with light</l>
                  <l>As with a garment, come at firſt in ſight,</l>
                  <l>He would haue then beene knowne vnto his foe,</l>
                  <l>And none haue dar'd once to exchange a blow</l>
                  <l>That he might therefore come vnto the fight</l>
                  <l>Vnknowne, this King of Iſrael had him dight</l>
                  <l>In ſtrange aray: A Stable was his Throne,</l>
                  <l>A Cratch his Cradle, His attendance none,</l>
                  <l>With hunger, thirſt, diſgrace, and pouerty,</l>
                  <l>Our Sauiour couered his diuinity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe here full low he in a Cratch doth lie,</l>
                  <l>Who ſometimes on the winged wind doth flie,<note place="margin">Eſai. 66. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And he whoſe throne is heau'n, whoſe footſtoole earth</l>
                  <l>Hath but a ſordid Stable at his Birth:</l>
                  <l>O had not man layne miſerably defil'd</l>
                  <l>In ſinnes polluted Stable, this faire Child</l>
                  <l>Had found a better lodging, but 'twas fit</l>
                  <l>That he which is our food, the ſweeteſt bit</l>
                  <l>That euer mortall taſted, ſhould be laid</l>
                  <l>In a poore Manger, ſince it may be ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Men were turn'd worſe then beaſts, and therefore they<note place="margin">Bernard.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be refreſht as beaſts that feede on Hay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ancient Prophets had foretold of yore</l>
                  <l>That Bethlehem was the place whereas ybore,</l>
                  <l>Should the <hi>Meſſias</hi> been: the learned read</l>
                  <l>The word to ſignifie the houſe of bread:</l>
                  <l>Whether becauſe for fruitefulneſſe and food,</l>
                  <l>It as a ſtore-houſe to the countrey ſtood,</l>
                  <l>So 'mongſt the ancient Romans Sicily<note place="margin">Horreum Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae. Tully.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was ſometimes called the barne of Italy:</l>
                  <l>Or becauſe Chriſt true heauenly bread indeed,</l>
                  <l>Whereon our ſoules, and not our mouthes doe feed,</l>
                  <l>Was there brought forth, ſo fathers moralize,<note place="margin">Hierom. Gregory.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Indeed from him all bread that doth ſuffice</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19248:8"/>
                  <l>Our ſoules and bodies is deriu'd: he giues</l>
                  <l>Corporall bread, by which the body liues:</l>
                  <l>Doctrinall bread he alſo doth affoord,</l>
                  <l>And this we call his holy heauenly Word,</l>
                  <l>Bread Sacramentall, in which we receiue</l>
                  <l>Spiritually the Giuer, and conceiue</l>
                  <l>A bleſſed vnion made in a ſtrange faſhion,</l>
                  <l>By Faith, and not by tranſubſtantiation:</l>
                  <l>In fine, celeſtiall bread he doth diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>At his eternall Table, vnto thoſe</l>
                  <l>Which are his Seruants whoſe delicious taſting</l>
                  <l>Shall giue our bodies an immortall laſting.</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Ioſephs</hi> time the come of Aegypt land,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 41.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was without number, like the Ocean ſand,</l>
                  <l>Bethlem had greater plenty at Chriſts Birth,</l>
                  <l>For heere was bread to nouriſh all the earth,</l>
                  <l>And of more bleſt continuance: thoſe full cares</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Pharaohs</hi> countrey laſted but ſeuen yeares,</l>
                  <l>Leane famine then tooke place: our Bethlehems ſtore</l>
                  <l>(As inexhauſted) laſts for euermore:</l>
                  <l>There the Aegyptians when they wanted Cates,</l>
                  <l>Were faine to buy them at exceſſiue rates.</l>
                  <l>Heere Bread like to the Prophets Milke and Wine,<note place="margin">Eſai. 55. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>A man may purchaſe without price or coyne:</l>
                  <l>And therefore as all nations in their neede,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Ioſeph</hi> came for corne, whereon to feede:</l>
                  <l>So let all people vnto Bethlehem haſte,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeke out the true <hi>Ioſeph</hi> which is plac'd</l>
                  <l>By the celeſtiall <hi>Pharaoh</hi> o're the earth,</l>
                  <l>To furniſh men with corne, againſt the dearth</l>
                  <l>Threatning the ſoules deſtruction, who will giue</l>
                  <l>If they but aske, enough for them to liue</l>
                  <l>Heere, and heereafter, where they ſhall be fed,</l>
                  <l>In an eternall houſe of liuing bread.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19248:9"/>
                  <l>Thrice happy Bethlehem, thou bleſt houſe of bread</l>
                  <l>On whom the Sunne of glorie firſt did ſpread:</l>
                  <l>The comfortable beames of his man God</l>
                  <l>Vnited nature, and there made abode:</l>
                  <l>But O more happy they, within whoſe heart</l>
                  <l>Faith giues him ſecond birth, and will not part</l>
                  <l>With this bleſt ſtore, I would our ſoules might be</l>
                  <l>The Bethlehem of his Natiuity:</l>
                  <l>But ere this can be ſo, we muſt put on</l>
                  <l>Myſtically ſuch a condition,</l>
                  <l>As that place had: firſt Bethlehem did ſeeme</l>
                  <l>But little in extent, leſſe in eſteeme,</l>
                  <l>The leaſt of Iudahs thouſands: So muſt we,</l>
                  <l>If we expect a bleſt renaſcency<note place="margin">Micah. 5. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of Chriſt within our ſoules, or would inherit</l>
                  <l>The purchaſe of his all-ſufficient merit.</l>
                  <l>Be meane, and little in our owne eſteeme,</l>
                  <l>How great, how good ſoeuer we may ſeeme:</l>
                  <l>In others iudgement: euery Chriſtian knowes</l>
                  <l>That Chriſt a Lilly is, but ſuch as growes</l>
                  <l>In the low valley of an humble minde,<note place="margin">Cant. 2. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not on proud mountaine tops, and as we finde</l>
                  <l>Flouds run not vp ſteep cliffs, but through low grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds</l>
                  <l>Conueigh their current: So his Grace ſurrounds</l>
                  <l>With a ſweet ſtreame of goodneſſe, only thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Which like low bottomes humbly doe diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>Themſelues to that bleſt moiſture, we muſt then</l>
                  <l>If we would haue our Chriſt the beſt of men</l>
                  <l>Spiritually borne in vs, all agree</l>
                  <l>To be a Bethlehem in humility.</l>
                  <l>Againe we muſt be ſtorehouſes of bread,</l>
                  <l>To feed the hungry, he that doth not ſpread</l>
                  <l>A wing of mercy on the poore ſhall finde,</l>
                  <l>Chriſt will not houſe them there, the ſupple minde</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19248:9"/>
                  <l>Like pliant waxe, loues gentle fire muſt ſoften</l>
                  <l>Ere he imprint his ſeale, and we muſt often<note place="margin">Eccles. 11. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Caſt our bread on the waters, if we looke</l>
                  <l>That he which humane nature on him tooke,</l>
                  <l>To ſaue the world, while here we liue on earth,</l>
                  <l>Should haue within our hearts a ſecond birth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now was the Scepter tane from <hi>Iudahs</hi> hand,</l>
                  <l>Nor 'twixt his feete ſate he, who did command</l>
                  <l>The Lawes coerciue power: an argument<note place="margin">Gen. 49. 10.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The promis'd <hi>Shilo</hi> was already ſent</l>
                  <l>Blind Iew, which dazeled with abundant light,</l>
                  <l>Sit'ſt like a dull Aegyptian, in the night</l>
                  <l>Of ſoule-deluding error, could record</l>
                  <l>Of ancient Prophets, make thee giue thy Lord</l>
                  <l>No better welcome, wilt thou yet denie</l>
                  <l>This firme vnqueſtion'd truth obſtinate eye</l>
                  <l>Shut vp in wilfull blindneſſe, let the place</l>
                  <l>Where Chriſt was borne, the time when, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chaſe</l>
                  <l>This cloud of darkeneſſe, looke not ſtill in vaine</l>
                  <l>For thy Meſſias, who till all againe</l>
                  <l>Turne into <hi>Chaos,</hi> ſhall no more be ſent</l>
                  <l>What time for want of faith thou ſhalt be ſhent</l>
                  <l>And ſentenc'd to deſtruction, if in time,</l>
                  <l>Thy teares like Iordan waſh not out thy crime.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But as when <hi>Moſes</hi> was in Aegypt borne,<note place="margin">Exod. 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>He was of his owne mother as forlorne</l>
                  <l>Caſt out into the riuer, and there found</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter, who from being dround</l>
                  <l>Preſeru'd the Infant, and with tender care</l>
                  <l>Brought vp this foundling, as her wombe had bare,</l>
                  <l>That goodly Hebrew: So was Chriſt bereau'd</l>
                  <l>Of a glad welcome by the Iewes, receiu'd</l>
                  <l>By the now happier Gentiles, happier farre</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Abrahams</hi> iſſue, whom ſo bright a Starre</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19248:10"/>
                  <l>Cannot enlighten, but his word deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>And 'gainſt the Sun of glory ſhut their eyes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="Monday" type="daily_meditation">
               <head>Mondaies Meditation, or the ſecond <hi>Canto.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Magi come out of the Eaſt,</l>
                     <l>Vnto Ieruſalem, in queſt</l>
                     <l>Of the Meſſias, and enquire,</l>
                     <l>But meet not there their full deſire.</l>
                  </lg>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>BEhold while <hi>Gideons</hi> fleece, the Iuyce is dry,<note place="margin">Iugd. 6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>His floore (the Gentiles) doth it ſelfe apply</l>
                  <l>To drinke the heauenly dew: From Hebers land</l>
                  <l>A countrey farre in the eaſt parts did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>But in what place vncertaine, whether Perſia,</l>
                  <l>Neerer Chaldea, or the fartheſt India,</l>
                  <l>(Each haue their ſeuerall authors) did ſend forth<note place="margin">Primitiae Gentium. <hi>Auguſtin.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Theſe firſt fruits of the Gentile (whoſe high worth</l>
                  <l>Makes them thought kings by ſome) I dare not ſay</l>
                  <l>Only from thence they came, from whence the day</l>
                  <l>Breakes, and <hi>Aurora</hi> chaſes thence blacke night,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Sol</hi> firſt riſing ſhewes his glorious light,</l>
                  <l>And guilds the lofty mountaines, whence his beames</l>
                  <l>Reflect a brightneſſe on the eaſterne ſtreames.</l>
                  <l>Whether theſe wiſe men came from <hi>Abrahams</hi> line,</l>
                  <l>Yet not of <hi>Sarahs</hi> off-ſpring, ſome aſſigne</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Keturah</hi> their grand-mother, or begot</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Baalams</hi> ſucceſſor, or tis not</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19248:10"/>
                  <l>Materiall to examine, ſo to lay</l>
                  <l>For firme poſition, were to much to ſay:</l>
                  <l>Whether they were Magicians as ſome thinke,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch who for deepe ſcience choſe to linke</l>
                  <l>Their Soules to Satan, or Philoſophers</l>
                  <l>Morall and naturall, or Aſtronomers,</l>
                  <l>(To which opinion I aſſent thus farre,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe we finde God call'd them by a ſtarre</l>
                  <l>I liſt not to examine may't ſuffice,</l>
                  <l>They haue this only title they were wiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wiſe men indeed, it is true wiſedomes lore,</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke for Chriſt, and neuer to giue ore</l>
                  <l>Till we haue found him, ſo did theſe that came</l>
                  <l>Out from the Eaſt, would we could doe the ſame.</l>
                  <l>It is a rare thing to be skil'd in arts</l>
                  <l>Abſtruſeſt cunning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to haue all parts</l>
                  <l>That better humane knowledge, but to know</l>
                  <l>Chriſt, is more worth, then all that art can ſhow:</l>
                  <l>And therefore as when <hi>Phoebus</hi> 'gins to riſe,</l>
                  <l>The ſtarres ecclipſed luſtre hidden lies</l>
                  <l>From eye of mortall; So when as diuine</l>
                  <l>Soule-quickning wiſedome, as the Sun doth ſhine,</l>
                  <l>Each humane ſcience like a petty ſtarre,</l>
                  <l>Muſt vaile vnto it: as a ſhip from farre</l>
                  <l>Spying the Kings ride on the narrow ſeas,</l>
                  <l>When ſhe comes neere (though little for her eaſe)</l>
                  <l>Bends her proud head, and doth withouten faile,</l>
                  <l>In moſt ſubmiſſiue manner ſtrike her Sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</l>
                  <l>See here the (ne're enough to be admir'd)</l>
                  <l>Attractiue power of Chriſt, by which enſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd</l>
                  <l>To finde their Sauiour out, with ioyfull hearts</l>
                  <l>Theſe Magi come from the remoteſt parts:</l>
                  <l>The Sun doth not exhale more forcibly</l>
                  <l>The pureſt vapours vp, the Loadſtone nigh</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19248:11"/>
                  <l>The Sympathetique ſteele, makes it not cling,</l>
                  <l>More cloſe vnto it, then this heauenly King,</l>
                  <l>(His innate vertue did ſuch loue diſtill)</l>
                  <l>Made their affections cleaue vnto his will.<note place="margin">2. King. 10.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>That Sheba's Queene drawne by the bare report</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Salomons</hi> faire vertue, left her Court,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Iudah's</hi> countrey may full ſtrange appeare,</l>
                  <l>But ſee then <hi>Salomon</hi> a greater heere.<note place="margin">Luke 11. 31.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>More ſtrange to Chriſt the comming of thoſe wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Then hers to <hi>Salomon</hi> we muſt agnize:</l>
                  <l>She was but one alone, they many were,</l>
                  <l>She but a woman, they men, ſhe came there</l>
                  <l>Led by the tongue of Fame, but they from farre</l>
                  <l>Were guided by the leading of a ſtarre:</l>
                  <l>She came to one whoſe riper yeeres did ſpeake</l>
                  <l>Him growne to mans eſtate: they to a weake</l>
                  <l>And tender Infant: She to one that ſwaid</l>
                  <l>A royall Scepter; They to one was laid</l>
                  <l>In a poore Manger; She came but to trie</l>
                  <l>The truth of Fame, and curiouſly to ſpie</l>
                  <l>His ſtate and knowledge, in effect meere vanity:</l>
                  <l>They to adore their God in his humanity:</l>
                  <l>In fine we finde her comming is expreſt</l>
                  <l>From forth the South: but theirs is from the eaſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like as the Sun when he doth firſt diſplay</l>
                  <l>His radiant luſtre, and with lightſome day</l>
                  <l>Breake from the Eaſt, and getting in his throne</l>
                  <l>Fixt in the middle of the heauenly Zone,</l>
                  <l>Makes his diurnall progreſſe to the Weſt,</l>
                  <l>And then returnes againe into the Eaſt:</l>
                  <l>So thoſe wiſe men doe firſt their iourney gin,</l>
                  <l>From out the Eaſt nor did they euer lin;</l>
                  <l>Till to Ieruſalem the Weſt they came,</l>
                  <l>And fitly may this occidentall name</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19248:11"/>
                  <l>Be giuen to it, ſince the glorious Sun</l>
                  <l>Of righteouſneſſe hauing his courſe runne,</l>
                  <l>Did there ſit red and bloudy, there he died,</l>
                  <l>Who for the ſinne of man was crucified,</l>
                  <l>From thence they Eaſtward paſſe, and neuer ceaſe</l>
                  <l>Till to their countrey they come backe in peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of all the parts in the worlds continent</l>
                  <l>The Eaſt hath aye beene held moſt excellent.</l>
                  <l>Whether becauſe that fruitfull Paradice,</l>
                  <l>Was planted Eaſtward or that Sol doth riſe</l>
                  <l>There in his glory, or that the day ſpring</l>
                  <l>Is made an attribute to heauens great King:<note place="margin">Luke 1. 78.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hence is it that in Churches (when addreſt</l>
                  <l>In Prayer to God) we looke vnto the Eaſt.</l>
                  <l>Either becauſe the earths moſt honoured part<note place="margin">Iustin Martyr.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To the Almighties worſhip we conuert:</l>
                  <l>Or becauſe Paradice, which Eaſtward ſtood,</l>
                  <l>Loſt firſt by Adam's fall, and ſince made good<note place="margin">Greg. Nyſſe.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>By Chriſt our Sauiour, we by looke deſire:</l>
                  <l>Or cauſe the Lambe of God, which did expire</l>
                  <l>Vpon the Croſſe, extended to the Weſt,<note place="margin">Damaſcen.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>We to behold him looke into the Eaſt;</l>
                  <l>For many cauſes which might be aſſign'd,</l>
                  <l>This quarter of the World, the Eaſt, we find</l>
                  <l>In high repute, of which the leaſt in worth</l>
                  <l>Is not, that ſuch wiſe men it did bring forth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well doth the title with the place accord,</l>
                  <l>Wiſe from the Eaſt, for eaſterne parts affoord</l>
                  <l>Beſt intellectuals: ſo when holy writ</l>
                  <l>Would <hi>Salomon</hi> commend for rareſt wit,</l>
                  <l>This Elogie it giues, he did exceede,<note place="margin">1. King. 4. 30.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The beſt of thoſe, which the Eaſt parts did breede:</l>
                  <l>As if the men which did inhabite there,</l>
                  <l>Then all the reſt of mortals wiſer were,</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:19248:12"/>
                  <l>Which commonly is ſo, either becauſe</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Phoebus</hi> neere vicinity, which drawes</l>
                  <l>Groſſe vapours thence, and by his quickning ray,</l>
                  <l>Refines the fluent bloud, whoſe pure allay</l>
                  <l>Giues vigour to the Spirits: So we ſee</l>
                  <l>That Plants by Gardners carefull induſtry</l>
                  <l>Set, that the morning Sun may on them glow,</l>
                  <l>Doe ſooneſt ripe, and to perfection grow:</l>
                  <l>So natures well red ſecretaries ſay,</l>
                  <l>That in the morne of all times, of the day,</l>
                  <l>The faireſt Pearles are generate, and moſt bright</l>
                  <l>Then ſhines the gold Excelling <hi>Chryſolite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or happely in wiſedome they excell,</l>
                  <l>Cauſe our firſt Parents in the Eaſt did dwell,</l>
                  <l>And might to their Succeſſors, more confin'd</l>
                  <l>Some monuments of knowledge leaue behind,</l>
                  <l>How fitly come they from the Eaſt, t'expreſſe</l>
                  <l>The riſing of the Sun of righteouſneſſe:</l>
                  <l>And with the glad report of this bright morrow<note place="margin">Bernard.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To chaſe from humane hearts the night of ſorrow,</l>
                  <l>From thence they come, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence the day is borne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Phoebus</hi> hides the bluſhes of the morne,</l>
                  <l>That from the place where the day gins to cleare,<note place="margin">Chryſost.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Faith the ſoules day-light alſo might appeare</l>
                  <l>Where after Adam was create of earth,</l>
                  <l>Gan humane bodies firſt to haue their birth,</l>
                  <l>After our bleſſed Sauiours Incarnation,</l>
                  <l>The ſoule did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> receiue Regeneration,</l>
                  <l>Where ſinne and nature firſt beginning had,</l>
                  <l>There G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and truth ariſe, where miſchiefe clad</l>
                  <l>In mercies habite did firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ine man</l>
                  <l>His bleſſed reparation there began</l>
                  <l>Indeede 'twas fit that part which did begin</l>
                  <l>To poiſon humane nature with foule ſin,</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:19248:12"/>
                  <l>Should ſend forth thoſe that did in Grace excell,</l>
                  <l>And of a generall Antidote foretell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Within the heart of Iudahs fertile land,</l>
                  <l>Salem the ſoiles Metropolis did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Builded by <hi>Shem,</hi> the Magi to this place,</l>
                  <l>Arriue, in hope to ſee their Sauiours face;</l>
                  <l>And where indeed on humane ſtate to ground,</l>
                  <l>Was the Meſſias likelier to be found,</l>
                  <l>To ſee the King where could they haue opinion,</l>
                  <l>If not in the chiefe ſeate of his Dominion:</l>
                  <l>To finde the heart, they that body the enter,</l>
                  <l>Seeke out the midſt, becauſe there lies the Center.</l>
                  <l>Chriſt was our head, and where could men expect</l>
                  <l>Him, but in <hi>Shem's</hi> faire Citty, which erect</l>
                  <l>Aboue the reſt in Iudah, did ſo ſtand</l>
                  <l>As doth the head the body to command<note place="margin">Ioſephus.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ieruſalem the viſion of peace</l>
                  <l>Imports, as Learned ſay, ſterne warre did ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>When Chriſt was borne, where the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could make abode</l>
                  <l>Better then in Ieruſalem the God</l>
                  <l>Of Peace and Mercie? Was not there the Court?</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould the King be abſent? the reſort</l>
                  <l>Of Prieſts was thither; there the Altar ſtood,</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould not Chriſt the Sacrifice, whoſe bloud</l>
                  <l>Did expiate our ſinnes, be alſo there?</l>
                  <l>There was the Temple, whoſe faire frame vpreare</l>
                  <l>Did <hi>Salomon</hi> the wiſe, but ſince deſpoyld</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> in greater beauty did rebuild:</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould not then the Temples God abide</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a place, ſo highly beautified?</l>
                  <l>To queſtion this no more, 'twas Gods beheſt,</l>
                  <l>Nor are the greateſt places ſtill the beſt:</l>
                  <l>Experience tells vs, Chriſt is ſometimes found</l>
                  <l>In a poore ſmoakie cottage, when the ground</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:19248:13"/>
                  <l>Of goodly Palaces, pau'd with faireſt ſtone,</l>
                  <l>And Roomes of choiſeſt beauty ſtand alone</l>
                  <l>Vnuiſited by him, he may receiue</l>
                  <l>Birth in a petty cottage, while him reaue</l>
                  <l>Of life a city doth: So was it here,</l>
                  <l>As plaine in ſacred Story doth appeare:</l>
                  <l>Bethlehem at firſt into the world him ſent,</l>
                  <l>Ieruſalem out of the world him hent,</l>
                  <l>I'th firſt of theſe a cradle he did ſinde,</l>
                  <l>But in the laſt a Graue was him aſſign'd,</l>
                  <l>Borne, though obſcurely borne, at Bethlehem,</l>
                  <l>And crucified at Ieruſalem:</l>
                  <l>The wiſe men then at Salem may enquire,</l>
                  <l>But ſhall not there find out their Soules deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But why, O Lord, ſince there thou waſt not then,</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou permit thoſe well deuoted men</l>
                  <l>To wander from their way, and goe about,</l>
                  <l>Protracting time in ſeeking of thee out:</l>
                  <l>Did their owne error leade them from the way?</l>
                  <l>And thou in iuſtice ſuffer them to ſtray?</l>
                  <l>Subtracting from them thy ſtarres glorious light,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Becauſe they truſted more to humane might,</l>
                  <l>Then thy aſſiſting power: into my thought</l>
                  <l>It cannot ſinke, that ignorance then brought</l>
                  <l>But their all carefull prouidence, whoſe hand</l>
                  <l>Makes all our actions waite on thy command:</l>
                  <l>Perhaps it was thy will theſe men ſhould come</l>
                  <l>Firſt, to Ieruſalem, leſt they ſhould rome</l>
                  <l>Vncertainely about, for their records</l>
                  <l>Of ancient Prophets, kept, could ſhew the Lords</l>
                  <l>Moſt certaine place of birth and as one ſaith</l>
                  <l>Informe their knowledge and confirme their Faith:<note place="margin">Chryſost.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or it may be as Legates thou didſt ſend</l>
                  <l>Theſe Magi vnto Salem, to the end</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:19248:13"/>
                  <l>The Iewes might their Meſſias Birth diſcerne,</l>
                  <l>And theſe teach others, while they ſeeke to learne,</l>
                  <l>Or was it not to ſtirre vp <hi>Iſaacs</hi> Line,</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke their Sauiour out, when thus combine<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>They ſaw the Gentiles: or as ſome conclude</l>
                  <l>To argue them of foule ingratitude,</l>
                  <l>Who would not their Meſſias entertaine<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom they ſaw ſtrangers ſeeke with ſo much paine?</l>
                  <l>O let not vs like theſe hard-hearted Iewes</l>
                  <l>Out of a wilfull blindneſſe thus refuſe</l>
                  <l>Grace freely offred, let theſe wiſer men</l>
                  <l>Leade vs by their example, how and when</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke out Chriſt, but yet take heed their faſhion</l>
                  <l>Be not abus'd by apiſh imitation:</l>
                  <l>As 'tis by Ieſuited Rome, which drawes</l>
                  <l>From hence her pilgrimage to Saints, becauſe</l>
                  <l>The Magi come to Salem, who indeed</l>
                  <l>Their action giues no countenance, nor our Creed</l>
                  <l>Warrant to this deuice, for but compare</l>
                  <l>The Romaniſts with them, and they will ſhare</l>
                  <l>No correſpondencie at all, vnleſſe</l>
                  <l>A kinde of poore reſemblance they expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>In their long iourneys, and their larger gifts,</l>
                  <l>They offer at their ſhrines, impotent ſhifts</l>
                  <l>For their groſſe Idoll worſhip; firſt we know</l>
                  <l>The wiſe men taught by God to Salem goe,</l>
                  <l>He bleſt that iourney which they had begun,</l>
                  <l>And ſent a Starre to leade them to a Sun:</l>
                  <l>Theſe haue no ſtarre at all, the heauenly Word,</l>
                  <l>That light vnto our feet, doth them afford</l>
                  <l>No helpe in all their iourney, ne haue they</l>
                  <l>The ſtarre of Faith to guide them in the way:</l>
                  <l>Blind zeale may hale them forward, or perchance</l>
                  <l>Humane tradition may it ſelfe aduance</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19248:14"/>
                  <l>But as a wandring Plannet, no true guide,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe the like doth vnto them betide,</l>
                  <l>Which doth to thoſe, who iourneying in the night</l>
                  <l>Eſpie an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> whoſe falſe light</l>
                  <l>Leads them ore ditch and hedge, though dirt &amp; mire,</l>
                  <l>His maine inuention is iuſt ſuch a fire,</l>
                  <l>Deluding thoſe that follow it, let me ſay</l>
                  <l>Romes Pilgrimes are thus guided in their way:</l>
                  <l>Againe the Magi ſeeke for Chriſt alone,<note place="margin">Mat. 2. 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where's <hi>Judahs</hi> King? O ſhew vs him or none<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereas the Romiſh Pilgrimes Chriſt forſake,</l>
                  <l>And for their Sauiour vnto Saints them take:</l>
                  <l>The wiſe men came Chriſt liuing to behold;</l>
                  <l>Theſe but dead rotten reliques to vnfold:</l>
                  <l>They came to worſhip God; theſe idle drones</l>
                  <l>Come but to worſhip ſenceleſſe ſtocks and ſtones:</l>
                  <l>Shall we then ſay, theſe imitate the wiſe?</l>
                  <l>Alas, I cannot, no we muſt deuiſe</l>
                  <l>To follow them a better way then this,</l>
                  <l>Or finde we ſhall not, cauſe we ſeeke amiſſe:</l>
                  <l>And would ye know, wherein to imitate</l>
                  <l>Theſe bleſſed Magi? Let it be in that</l>
                  <l>Which is praiſe-worthy, as their care and paine,</l>
                  <l>To finde out Chriſt, for as the learned ſaine,</l>
                  <l>They tooke their iourney when the colder ayre,</l>
                  <l>Chang'd dewes to froſts, when winters ſiluer haire</l>
                  <l>Stucke full of Snow, and <hi>Boreas</hi> bitter breath</l>
                  <l>Blew numbneſſe on their limbs: yet did pale death</l>
                  <l>Stand, as the Angell ſtood in <hi>Balaams</hi> way<note place="margin">Numb. 22.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>With a drawne Sword, their bodies he might ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Not their affections, they went forward ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Chooſing to die, rather then want their will,</l>
                  <l>Like them, ſo vs no rub, no barre ſhould hold</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Iudahs</hi> King: As couetous for gold,</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19248:14"/>
                  <l>Ambitious after honour: So muſt we</l>
                  <l>Seeke Chriſt, with feruour and alacrity:</l>
                  <l>Religion is not bred in ſloth and eaſe,</l>
                  <l>The ſweat of labour, ere ſhe God can pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſit vpon her brow: yet ſee we are</l>
                  <l>Happy in this, we need not iourney farre</l>
                  <l>To finde Chriſt out, our lot ſo faire doth ſtand,</l>
                  <l>That we may ſtill keepe in our natiue land,</l>
                  <l>And meet our wiſhes, Chriſt is to be found</l>
                  <l>Within our Kingdome, in the hallowed ground,</l>
                  <l>Whereon our Temples ſtand, each Sacrament,</l>
                  <l>May euery good ſoule is his continent:</l>
                  <l>Yet we to finde him out (ſo meane our care)</l>
                  <l>More ſlow then <hi>Snailes,</hi> more lame then Cripples ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</l>
                  <l>O how ſhall the great care and diligence</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe, condemne our ſloth and negligence?</l>
                  <l>How ſhould we feare, ſince in offence we ſtand</l>
                  <l>Equall with <hi>Iudah,</hi> Gods all-powerfull hand</l>
                  <l>Should throw downe vengeance on vs, and our eyes</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt that faire light which now they doe deſpiſe.</l>
                  <l>The countrey of theſe Magi was the Eaſt,</l>
                  <l>And commonly men loue their owne ſoile beſt,</l>
                  <l>Yet ready preſt they in obedience ſtand,</l>
                  <l>To leaue (as <hi>Abraham</hi> did) their natiue land:</l>
                  <l>When that bleſt Maid and Mother loſt her ſonne,</l>
                  <l>At her returne from Salem, as vndone</l>
                  <l>Without him (who can haue ſo great a loſſe</l>
                  <l>And not goe home againe by weeping croſſe?)</l>
                  <l>She ſought him ſorrowing 'mongſt her friends &amp; kin,<note place="margin">Luke 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But could not finde him, ſhe might there begin</l>
                  <l>Her ſearch anew, Chriſt is not alwayes found</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt kindred and acquaintance, if the ground</l>
                  <l>That gaue vs birth, will not our Lord receiue,</l>
                  <l>For him we muſt our natiue countrey leaue,</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:19248:15"/>
                  <l>Our Friends, our home, and ſtranger places greet,</l>
                  <l>Though our owne <hi>Jthaca</hi> be nere ſo ſweet.</l>
                  <l>Thrice happy is that man, which can with theſe</l>
                  <l>Forſake his ſoile, banniſh neglect and eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Goe from the Eaſt of pleaſure, till he finde</l>
                  <l>Ieruſalem, that is, the peace of minde.</l>
                  <l>Now had the Magi found this City out,</l>
                  <l>Where Sion ſtood, and walking round about,</l>
                  <l>(Not to ſuruay the building or behold</l>
                  <l>The ſtately Temple, richly deckt with gold)</l>
                  <l>Enquire for <hi>Iudahs</hi> King, her new borne King,</l>
                  <l>This ſeem'd to <hi>Jſaacs</hi> Line an vncouth thing,</l>
                  <l>They knew the Scepter was from <hi>Iudah</hi> gone,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Herod</hi> who was now their King, was one</l>
                  <l>Inaugur'd by the Romanes, therefore they</l>
                  <l>Pos'd by this queſtion, knew not what to ſay:</l>
                  <l>But the wiſe men the more they found them ſlow,</l>
                  <l>To anſwer, were the more inflam'd to know:</l>
                  <l>Tell vs we pray (for we deſire to learne)</l>
                  <l>Where liues this Infant King? we can diſcerne</l>
                  <l>No ſigne of ioy, to make vs thinke him heere:</l>
                  <l>O then where is he? we account not deare</l>
                  <l>Our trauell or expence, ſo we may gaine</l>
                  <l>The long-wiſht ſight of <hi>Iudahs</hi> Soueraigne:</l>
                  <l>That he is borne, we doe true tidings bring,</l>
                  <l>Borne yours, your promis'd, your expected King,</l>
                  <l>Borne in your Countrey, what we ſpeake we know,</l>
                  <l>What we haue ſeene we willingly will ſhow,</l>
                  <l>We haue his ſtarre ſeene, whoſe vnuſuall light,</l>
                  <l>Shone in our eaſterne climate, and made night</l>
                  <l>Excell the day in beauty: There's no cauſe</l>
                  <l>You ſhould ſuſpect we come to breake your Lawes,</l>
                  <l>Or to inuade your Kingdome, for we bring</l>
                  <l>No armed troupes to ſet vpon your King,</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:19248:15"/>
                  <l>VVe doe not come as ſpies, to vnderſtand</l>
                  <l>The fruitfulneſſe and ſtrength of this your land,</l>
                  <l>Our trauell is not to encreaſe our wealth,</l>
                  <l>By traffique with you, or by priuate ſtealth</l>
                  <l>To get your treaſure, ſee, we bring great ſtore</l>
                  <l>Of coſtly ſpices, and rich Indian Ore,</l>
                  <l>Vnto this royall Infant to preſent,</l>
                  <l>Which with ſubmiſſiue reuerence our intent</l>
                  <l>Is to lay downe before him, and fallow</l>
                  <l>Our ſelues before his footeſtoole, for we know</l>
                  <l>That more then man is in him, and are come</l>
                  <l>Thus farre to worſhip him: This is the ſumme</l>
                  <l>Of all our wiſhes, let but your report</l>
                  <l>Be our direction, to this Princes Court:</l>
                  <l>This ſaid they ceaſt, but none can them reſolue</l>
                  <l>In their demand, which doth their ſoules inuolue</l>
                  <l>VVith a new cloud of ſorrow, in which plight</l>
                  <l>A while I leaue them, till a clearer light</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nfuſe more knowledge, time ere long will bring</l>
                  <l>The deuout Magi, to this new borne King.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="Tuesday" type="daily_meditation">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:19248:16"/>
               <head>Tueſdaies Meditation, or the third <hi>Canto.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Herod</hi> and his the Newes appalls,</l>
                     <l>The King in haste a counſell calls:</l>
                     <l>Next to conferre in ſecret wiſe,</l>
                     <l>He with the Magi doth deuiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>BY this time ſame hauing new impt her wings,</l>
                  <l>Flies from the City to the Court, and brings</l>
                  <l>Newes of theſe mens arriuall, and the end</l>
                  <l>Of their intended iourney: to commend</l>
                  <l>Their diligence Court-Paraſites will ſtriue,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> and <hi>Cuſhi,</hi> who ſhall thriue<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Sam. 18.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beſt in their expedition: Princes eares</l>
                  <l>Doe like their hands reach farre, and tyrants feares</l>
                  <l>Place Spies in euery corner, whoſe cloſe art</l>
                  <l>Sliely inſinuates into the Heart,</l>
                  <l>Of the abuſed Subiect, and from thence</l>
                  <l>Drawes danger on his head, vnder pretence</l>
                  <l>Of more then common kindeneſſe, what he find<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sincerely ſpoken from plaine meaning minds,</l>
                  <l>He poyſons in report, when he it beares</l>
                  <l>To his Kings greedy, all-ſuſpecting eares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>After this tatling goddeſſe once had ſpread</l>
                  <l>This Newes abroad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and buz'd into the head</l>
                  <l>Of fawning Sycophants, a pick-thanke tale,</l>
                  <l>Looke how a ſhip driuen with a fore-right gale</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:19248:16"/>
                  <l>Cuts through the Ocean: they hie faſt to court,</l>
                  <l>And to ſterne <hi>Herod</hi> make a loud report.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No ſooner had fame toucht the tyrants eare,</l>
                  <l>But that his coward bloud gaue way to feare,</l>
                  <l>To take poſſeſſion of him, that he ſtood</l>
                  <l>Aſtoniſht at the newes: the raging floud</l>
                  <l>VVhen the fierce winds impetuouſly doe blow,</l>
                  <l>And in their vnreſiſted fury throw</l>
                  <l>The angry billowes, 'gainſt the ſandy ſhore</l>
                  <l>Spits not out ſome, or doth more loudly roare,</l>
                  <l>Then vexed <hi>Herod,</hi> who did inly burne,</l>
                  <l>VVhen ycie feare to fiery rage did turne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like as a ſiluer Current, whoſe cleare ſtrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhen ſweetly guilded by the lightſome beame</l>
                  <l>Of gold-lockt <hi>Phoebus,</hi> it reflects a light,</l>
                  <l>Becomes a pleaſant obiect to the ſight,</l>
                  <l>But if ſome ruder Swaine diſturbe the floud</l>
                  <l>By taking in it, fetching dirt and mud</l>
                  <l>The water thickens, and begins to looke</l>
                  <l>More like a foule ſinke, then a chriſt all b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ooke:</l>
                  <l>So while the riuer of man's life runs cleare,</l>
                  <l>And Sun-like reaſon, from his lofty ſpheare</l>
                  <l>Guilds it with beauty, 'tis a precious thing,</l>
                  <l>Surpaſſing Thames and Iſis, or that ſpring</l>
                  <l>VVhich fond <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rciſſus</hi> in his iourney found,</l>
                  <l>In which the ſelfe-admiring Boy was drown'd,</l>
                  <l>But if that paſſion eaſie paſſage finde,</l>
                  <l>It ſoone diſturbs the quiet of the minde,</l>
                  <l>Then the Conceit growes muddy to the brinke,</l>
                  <l>Like puddle, bad to view, but worſe to drinke.</l>
                  <l>So ſtood the caſe with <hi>Herod,</hi> and indeed</l>
                  <l>Suſpicious Tirants ſeldome better ſpeed:</l>
                  <l>A <hi>panicke</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>out takes them oftentimes,</l>
                  <l>VVhen none ſeeke to offend them, but their crimes:</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:19248:17"/>
                  <l>And reaſon good, for this truth hath beene ſaid,</l>
                  <l>He whom all feare, of all muſt be afraid:<note place="margin">Seneca.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>O heauy burthen of a Monarches crowne,</l>
                  <l>O Pillow ſtuft with thornes, and not with dowlne,</l>
                  <l>O glorious bondage ſeldome bleſt with age,</l>
                  <l>O lofty building ſubiect to the rage</l>
                  <l>Of ſtorme and tempeſt, O faire guilded Cup</l>
                  <l>Containing poiſon, who would take thee vp,</l>
                  <l>(So once a Macedonianking did ſay,)<note place="margin">Antigonus</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though he ſhould ſtumble on thee in the way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As a faire roome at ſome great nuptiall feaſt</l>
                  <l>Hung with rich <hi>Arras,</hi> and each corner dreſt</l>
                  <l>With coſtly furniture, heere goodly plate,</l>
                  <l>There curious glaſſes, all ſet out in ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Tables well wrought, with perfum'd damaske couer'd,</l>
                  <l>Embroder'd ſtooles, nothing amiſſe or ſlubber'd,</l>
                  <l>By ſome rude fray of the diſtemper'd gueſt</l>
                  <l>(As with the <hi>Centaures</hi> at the <hi>Lapythes</hi> Feaſt)<note place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Becomes diſordered, ſo that all the frame</l>
                  <l>Nought but a <hi>Chaos</hi> you can iuſtly name:</l>
                  <l>Such a confuſed heape was <hi>Iudah's</hi> King,</l>
                  <l>When fame humming about his eares, did ſting</l>
                  <l>His very heart and ſoule, with the report</l>
                  <l>Of a new riuall, to his Crowne and Court.</l>
                  <l>Now gan remembrance of his Tyrant raigne</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o torture him with an vnwonted paine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he ſtormie rage which on his ſubiects fell</l>
                  <l>He thinkes they will reuenge, and now rebell,</l>
                  <l>Diſmaid at this, he doth begin to moane him,</l>
                  <l>As if they came already to dethrone him:</l>
                  <l>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>e is an ill Interpreter of things,</l>
                  <l>Eſpecially within the hearts of kings:</l>
                  <l>He thinkes that ſtrangers will inuade his land</l>
                  <l>In hoſtile manner, and with powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>full hand,</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:19248:17"/>
                  <l>Expell him thence, and in his ſeate aduance</l>
                  <l>The new borne Infant: then he ſees a glance</l>
                  <l>Of a great Perſian Hoſte, that hard at hand,</l>
                  <l>Haue got already at their full command</l>
                  <l>The bulwarke of his kingdome, Salems towne,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe the Magi durſt not vp and downe</l>
                  <l>Make ſuch enquiry, quite againſt his will,</l>
                  <l>Who with a very frowne was wont to kill:</l>
                  <l>Mou'd with the wind of different thoughts he raues,</l>
                  <l>Like the barke, beaten by the furious waues</l>
                  <l>Of the enchafed floud: the Deuill too</l>
                  <l>Exagitates his minde, yet doubtfull who</l>
                  <l>The new-borne Infant was: he knew decreed<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>A time in fate, wherein the womans ſeed</l>
                  <l>Should break the Serpents head: As when the queene</l>
                  <l>Of heauen, fiercely enrag'd with iealous ſpleene</l>
                  <l>Againſt <hi>Alcmena,</hi> and her Ioue-borne ſonne</l>
                  <l>From Affricke brought two <hi>Snakes</hi> to ſeaze vpon</l>
                  <l>His infant body, that their gripe ſo fierce</l>
                  <l>Might cauſe his cradle to become his Herſe,</l>
                  <l>But young <hi>Alcides</hi> made his tender hands</l>
                  <l>About the Serpents ſuch death-threatning bands,</l>
                  <l>They could not hurt him, ſqueeſing them ſo ſore,</l>
                  <l>That 'twixt his fingers a foule purple gore</l>
                  <l>Iſſued apace, in which their life was drown'd,</l>
                  <l>Then let them drop quite ſenceleſſe to the ground:</l>
                  <l>So ſtood the caſe, when as diſſention roſe</l>
                  <l>Bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ixt this royall Infant and his foes:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rod</hi> and <hi>Satan</hi> two foule Serpens were,</l>
                  <l>Whom this new <hi>Hercules</hi> did ſqueeſe with feare</l>
                  <l>Of his all-powerfull hand, they both did dread</l>
                  <l>Their kingdomes ruine, and by this were led</l>
                  <l>Into vnwonted troubles, <hi>Satan</hi> thought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>That this was he, by whom was to be wrought</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:19248:18"/>
                  <l>(As a new <hi>Moſes</hi>) Iſraels Redemption</l>
                  <l>From Hels proud <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and a full exemption</l>
                  <l>From all Aegyptian bondage, which oppreſſion</l>
                  <l>Lay heauie vpon man for his tranſgreſſion:</l>
                  <l>This troubled Satan in infernall ſhade,</l>
                  <l>And with new horrour did his thoughts inuade:</l>
                  <l>Like as the greedy wolfe, when as he ſpies</l>
                  <l>The carefull Shepheard neere, or heares the cries</l>
                  <l>Of the fierce Maſtife troubled therewithall,</l>
                  <l>A chilling feare his ſences doth apall:</l>
                  <l>So woluiſh Satan when he ſaw ſo neere,</l>
                  <l>The Shepheard of our ſoule, a deadly feare</l>
                  <l>Tooke hold vpon him, and diſturb'd him ſo,</l>
                  <l>As doth the preſence of a powerfull Foe</l>
                  <l>A weake opponent: rob'd of his content,</l>
                  <l>He vexes <hi>Herod</hi> his fit inſtrument,</l>
                  <l>Knowing that feare of ſuch a danger will</l>
                  <l>Stirre vp a care, how to preuent his ill,</l>
                  <l>Regardleſſe ſo he may ſecurely raigne</l>
                  <l>Though deepe in blood he doe his hand ingraine,</l>
                  <l>VVell hoping this diſtraction would him bring</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke the ruine of the new borne King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That ſuch a Tyrant ſhould ſo farre giue way</l>
                  <l>To his perplexed thoughts, and ſo diſmay</l>
                  <l>With feare of future troubles his weake minde,</l>
                  <l>Is not to be admir'd: But when I finde</l>
                  <l>That all Ieruſalem was rent in ſunder</l>
                  <l>With him in this ſtrange Paſſion, then I wonder</l>
                  <l>She, that as one or'eioy'd at this new birth</l>
                  <l>Should haue expreſt a triumph and with mirth</l>
                  <l>Haue crownd her browes, ſhe that doth repreſent</l>
                  <l>A peacefull city, and with full content</l>
                  <l>Should the great King of peace haue entertain'd,</l>
                  <l>Was at Chriſts birth, as in her trauell, paind.</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:19248:18"/>
                  <l>But wonder not, a Princes faſhion</l>
                  <l>Is ſoone obſeru'd by Subiects imitation:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cameleons</hi> cannot into colours turne</l>
                  <l>Faſter then Courtiers: if their Soueraigne mourne</l>
                  <l>Blacke clouds of ſorrow couer all their face,</l>
                  <l>If ſmile, they change their copie; 'tis a grace:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clyſophus</hi> thinkes to be without an eye,</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Philip</hi> be but blind: to goe awry</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Alexander</hi> doe ſo: Paraſites</l>
                  <l>Are iuſt like glaſſes to their Princes ſights,</l>
                  <l>Fitly reſembling euery looke they haue,</l>
                  <l>Merry or ſad, ridiculous or graue:</l>
                  <l>And as the Eccho anſwereth the voice<note place="margin">Iuuenal. Satyr. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>In the ſame tone it ſpeakes, if it reioyce</l>
                  <l>Sending forth ioyfull accents, if it ſorrow</l>
                  <l>Vtter, as ſad a language it doth borrow.</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Herods</hi> Courtiers Eccho-like, but ſound</l>
                  <l>What they receiue from him by a rebound:</l>
                  <l>Thus with him theſe (true royalties worſt bane)</l>
                  <l>Sea-like, or like the moone doe waxe and wane.</l>
                  <l>Another ſort of Courtiers, <hi>Herods</hi> friends</l>
                  <l>Did ſympathize with him, but in their ends</l>
                  <l>Much differing from the former, ſome did doubt</l>
                  <l>A new commenced warre, others more ſtout,</l>
                  <l>Expected alteration, for the Theame</l>
                  <l>It is beſt fiſhing in the troubled ſtreame,</l>
                  <l>Did whet deſire, onely they did not know</l>
                  <l>Which part to ſide on, when the ſtorme ſhould grow</l>
                  <l>And this perplext them: A third ſort there were</l>
                  <l>Of grauer Citizens; much diſmaid with feare,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Herod</hi> vexed at this ſtrange report</l>
                  <l>Would wreake his ſpleene on them: or if the court</l>
                  <l>Should change her King they fear'd a heauier yoake,</l>
                  <l>For ſeldome comes the better when the ſtroake</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19248:19"/>
                  <l>Falls from a farre-fetcht hand, it heauier lights</l>
                  <l>To haue an vnknowne Prince it euen affrights</l>
                  <l>Their vnderſtanding: As that vlcerous man,</l>
                  <l>Stucke full of flies, when ſome in pitty 'gan</l>
                  <l>To chace them thence, cryed out in piteous wiſe,</l>
                  <l>O doe not wrong me ſo, theſe full fed flies</l>
                  <l>Now ſated with my bloud, I well can beare,</l>
                  <l>But if you driue them thence, I much doe feare</l>
                  <l>New ones will fill their places, and the eaſe</l>
                  <l>You thinke to doe me, me farre more diſpleaſe:</l>
                  <l>So theſe thought better, with the ruſticke ſwaine</l>
                  <l>Once to digge vp <hi>Antigonus</hi> againe,</l>
                  <l>And to endu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e thoſe flies that had their fill,</l>
                  <l>Rather then new ones, which more bloud might ſwill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The common ſort ſeeing their ſoueraigne ſad,</l>
                  <l>Thought it their dutie alſo to be clad</l>
                  <l>In the minds mourning habite: Princes are</l>
                  <l>Like the firſt mouer to the lower ſtarre,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Subiects, by their ſwifter motion</l>
                  <l>They draw them ſtrongly to their owne deuotion:</l>
                  <l>And as a Horſe though full of force and ſpirit</l>
                  <l>Backt by a skilfull Rider ſeemes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>herite</l>
                  <l>His will and iudgement, one while ſtanding ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Then paci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g, running, bounding at his will,</l>
                  <l>So fares it twixt the Subiect and the King,</l>
                  <l>Backt by the Prince Rules ſnaffle doth him bring</l>
                  <l>To what his ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raigne pleaſe: the King's th' head,</l>
                  <l>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ubiect are the members, which doe ſpread</l>
                  <l>And grow from thence, now when the head's diſeaſ'd</l>
                  <l>How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hould the members but be much diſplea'd?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But here a doubt is mou'd, Muſt Subiects ſtill</l>
                  <l>Conforme their manners to their ſoueraignes will?</l>
                  <l>May not Ieruſalem with faire intent,</l>
                  <l>In this, or like perplexitie diſſent,</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19248:19"/>
                  <l>From troubled <hi>Herod,</hi> muſt the Princes faſhion</l>
                  <l>Still leade the Subiect to an imitation?</l>
                  <l>Not ſo, Kings are but men, and ſo may erre,</l>
                  <l>The King of Kigs Edict we muſt preferre</l>
                  <l>Before a mortals: though <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſay,</l>
                  <l>Doe this, if God forbide it, to obey</l>
                  <l>Is to become a traytor? Gods Command</l>
                  <l>Compar'd with mans, muſt like an Ocean ſtand,</l>
                  <l>To ſwallow vp that drop, to quench that ſparke,</l>
                  <l>As Idoll Dagon fell before the Arke;</l>
                  <l>As ſtarres are hidden when the Sun doth ſhine:</l>
                  <l>So humane lawes muſt ſtoope vnto diuine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The tyrant thus with feare perturb'd, at laſt</l>
                  <l>Summons his wits together, and doth caſt</l>
                  <l>How to preuent all danger, and in minde</l>
                  <l>Reuoluing many things, at length doth finde</l>
                  <l>No better courſe can with his ſafety ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Then by an Edict ſent throughout his land,</l>
                  <l>To call a counſell, and leſt by delay</l>
                  <l>He might incurre a hazzard, men that day</l>
                  <l>With ſpeciall writs to further his intent</l>
                  <l>Goe out, and ſummon ſtraight a Parlaiment:</l>
                  <l>In this, though elſe full of impietie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> to Kings a Preſident may be,</l>
                  <l>Not on their owne ſole iudgement to relie,</l>
                  <l>But to conſult with their graue counſels eie,</l>
                  <l>Which can ſee farre into high points of ſtate,</l>
                  <l>And deepeſt matters learnedly debate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well knew the cunning Tyrant how to make</l>
                  <l>A fit Election, and ſuch men to take</l>
                  <l>As his deſigne might further: for which cauſe</l>
                  <l>He conuocates the wiſeſt in the Lawes,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe whom he knew fitteſt to expound</l>
                  <l>Old Propheſies, and miſteries profound,</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19248:20"/>
                  <l>For Prieſts and Elders, with the learned Scribe,</l>
                  <l>He picks the beſt for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ame from euery Tribe:</l>
                  <l>Had warre the ſubiect beene to be diſcuſt,</l>
                  <l>He wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld haue cal'd Commanders for the truſt</l>
                  <l>Of mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iall matters, fits them beſt that are</l>
                  <l>Well ſeene and practiz'd in the feats of warre,</l>
                  <l>But this was no ſuch thing: <hi>Herods</hi> deſire</l>
                  <l>Was by all meanes he could deuiſe, t'exquire</l>
                  <l>Where he to whom ſo many ages paſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iudah's</hi> Dominion was aſſign'd at laſt</l>
                  <l>Should take his birth: the true Meſſias place</l>
                  <l>Was the maine queſtion that they had in chaſe.</l>
                  <l>They had not ſate in conſultation long,</l>
                  <l>But they were ſoone agreed, and yet among</l>
                  <l>So many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſcarce there cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d be one found out</l>
                  <l>To be their ſpeaker, and reſolue the doubt</l>
                  <l>At laſt an aged Prieſt did vndertake</l>
                  <l>To be the tongue for all the reſt, and make</l>
                  <l>A full relation of Prophetique truth,</l>
                  <l>So vp he ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and ſpake what next enſueth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Great Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g led ſure by ſome diuiner light.</l>
                  <l>From the blacke darkeneſſe and Cymmerian night</l>
                  <l>Of the Worlds error ſince ſtate pollicies</l>
                  <l>Thou leaueſt to ſearch out heauens high myſteries:</l>
                  <l>Happy are we thy ſubiects to behold</l>
                  <l>Such goodneſſe in ſuch greatneſſe, keepe thy hold,</l>
                  <l>Goe on in Grace and vertue though alone,</l>
                  <l>And thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, hold thy throne:</l>
                  <l>Know thou brig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Bethlehem is the place,</l>
                  <l>Which our M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſias c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en hath, to grace</l>
                  <l>With his maieſtqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> preſence, when he ſhall</l>
                  <l>Firſt ſee the light o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ball:</l>
                  <l>So write our ancient Prophets, 'mongſt the reſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ah,</hi> whoſe Oracles are thus expreſt:</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19248:20"/>
                  <l>And thou, O Bethlehem, in <hi>Iudahs</hi> Land,</l>
                  <l>Shalt not for leaſt among the Princes ſtand,</l>
                  <l>For out of thee ſhall come a King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which well</l>
                  <l>Shall know to guide my people Iſrael:</l>
                  <l>Thus in few words I doe my ſoueraigne ſhow,</l>
                  <l>What he with ſo much care deſir'd to know;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> well pleaſed with this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> beſtowed a nod,</l>
                  <l>And they their adoration, as ſome god</l>
                  <l>Had ſent them a rich fauour: then they kiſt</l>
                  <l>His hand, and ſo th' aſſembly was di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>miſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But I (though <hi>Herod</hi>) not diſmiſſe you ſo,</l>
                  <l>Something I haue to ſay before ye goe,</l>
                  <l>O can ye be ſo light, yet ſeeme ſo graue,</l>
                  <l>Profeſſe ſo much zeale, yet ſo little haue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can you to <hi>Herod</hi> truely point the place</l>
                  <l>Where your <hi>Meſſias</hi> is, yet want th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> grace</l>
                  <l>To viſite him you ſelues? As larger ſtones</l>
                  <l>Erected in ſome high way for the nounce,</l>
                  <l>Dir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct the Paſſenger, but doe not moue</l>
                  <l>A i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t from thence, where they were fixt in loue:</l>
                  <l>Or as the Bels loud repercuſſiue ſound</l>
                  <l>Cals vnto Church, neighbours that heare it round,</l>
                  <l>But in it ſelfe doth not leaſt motion feele,</l>
                  <l>To make it leaue it ſemicircled wheele:</l>
                  <l>So theſe could ſhew where Chriſt was to be found,</l>
                  <l>Yet neuer ſeeke him, all was ſhew and ſound,</l>
                  <l>No ſolid ſubſtance: They muſt needes be ill,</l>
                  <l>Who rich in knowledge, are ſo poore in will.</l>
                  <l>By this time <hi>Herod</hi> who in thought reuolu'd,</l>
                  <l>Many a Plot, and Plat-forme, was reſolu'd</l>
                  <l>To fixe on one for all: ſliely he ſent</l>
                  <l>For the wiſe men to court, with whom he ſpent</l>
                  <l>Some time in free diſcourſe, the maine thus farre</l>
                  <l>Did reach, to know what time the eaſterne ſtarre,</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:19248:21"/>
                  <l>Made his firſt appariſion, this once told</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> his minde did in theſe words vnfold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With how great care my ſelfe haue ſought to know</l>
                  <l>This Infant Prince ye come to, well doth ſhow</l>
                  <l>The counſell call'd of late, call'd for your good</l>
                  <l>For now we know the place of his aboad:</l>
                  <l>That he is more then humane I beleeue,</l>
                  <l>Though clouded in obſcurity, and grieue</l>
                  <l>Time and occaſion will not giue me leaue</l>
                  <l>To goe this progreſſe with you, and receiue</l>
                  <l>That ſoule ſecuring comfort, and delight</l>
                  <l>Which you will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eet with in the gracious ſight</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch an Obiect: but doe you goe on,</l>
                  <l>And ſearch with <hi>Linceus</hi> eyes, to light vpon</l>
                  <l>The houſe that holds him, and if once you fortune</l>
                  <l>(For which I will the higher powers importune)</l>
                  <l>But bring you to him, after you haue done</l>
                  <l>That you are led to by Deuotion,</l>
                  <l>Doe but ſo much of happy time afford,</l>
                  <l>As may returne you backe, to bring me word,</l>
                  <l>And I my ſelfe ſubmitting ſtate and glory,</l>
                  <l>Although to aftertimes I make a ſtory,</l>
                  <l>Will wing'd in my deſire approach before him,</l>
                  <l>And falling proſtrate on the ground adore him.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O ſubtile Fox, that with ſo faire pretence</l>
                  <l>Couldſt ſuch a deed of cruelty commence,</l>
                  <l>As the ſweete Infants murder, for we finde</l>
                  <l>Such Lambe-like ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> blance hid a woluiſh minde:</l>
                  <l>Of Chriſt the Lambe he ſpake, as if he meant</l>
                  <l>To worſhip, when to worry he was bent:</l>
                  <l>Hypocriſie with a fine thred is ſpunne,</l>
                  <l>And ſeemes an Eagle that dares face the Sunne,</l>
                  <l>But once expos'd vnto that glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ous light,</l>
                  <l>Shrinkes backe amaz'd, and canopies her ſight.</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:19248:21"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> by craft thought he might quickely gaine</l>
                  <l>What by plaine dealing he could not obtaine:</l>
                  <l>So Generalls in their exploits of warre,</l>
                  <l>Seeing the Lyons caſe will not reach farre,</l>
                  <l>That they may bring their Stratagem about</l>
                  <l>Peece on the Foxes skinne, to eke it out.</l>
                  <l>So the ſlie Fox as dead himſelfe doth lay,</l>
                  <l>When he intends to make the largeſt prey:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Ioab</hi> hugs him whom he meanes to ſlay,</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſſes whom he doth betray:</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Herods</hi> cunning doth himſelfe beguile,</l>
                  <l>The Wolfe delayes, the Lambe eſcapes the while:</l>
                  <l>The wiſe men lend an eare vnto the King,</l>
                  <l>But that we finde anſweare not any thing,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſince by ſilence they doe ſhew conſent,</l>
                  <l>They are diſmiſt, and <hi>Herod</hi> ſeems content.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="Wednesday" type="daily_meditation">
               <head>Wedneſdaies Meditation, or the fourth <hi>Canto.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By the ſtarres helpe the wiſe men finde</l>
                     <l>Our Sauiour out, their gifts defind,</l>
                     <l>Admoniſhed from God before</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Herods</hi> ſight they come no more.</l>
                  </lg>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Magi finding not what they doe lacke,</l>
                  <l>Vpon Ieruſalem ſoone turne their backe,</l>
                  <l>They had not trauail'd from the citty farre,</l>
                  <l>When the thrice welcome luſtre of their ſtarre</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:19248:22"/>
                  <l>Did reappeare vnto them: God withdrawes</l>
                  <l>His b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſings from vs, that a little pauſe</l>
                  <l>Of abſence may endeare them: ſo the light</l>
                  <l>To one immur'd in priſon ſeemes more bright</l>
                  <l>When his enlargement comes: ſo when the blaſt</l>
                  <l>Of ſome impetuous wind rends vp the Maſt</l>
                  <l>Of the Sea-toſſed-Hulke, ready as food</l>
                  <l>To ſtop the mouth of the deuouring flood,</l>
                  <l>A ſudden Calme is ſweeteſt: A diſeaſe</l>
                  <l>Makes health in the repurchaſt better pleaſe:</l>
                  <l>Viciſſitude delights, and breedes reſpect,</l>
                  <l>Where long enioying generates neglect.</l>
                  <l>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the wiſe men in all their iourney kept</l>
                  <l>The Starre a daily guide, they had not lept</l>
                  <l>For ioy, as they did now: indeed content</l>
                  <l>Might then haue kept pace with them, but as pent</l>
                  <l>Within too ſtrait a priſon, their vaſt ioy</l>
                  <l>Breakes forth into expreſſion, no annoy</l>
                  <l>Able to counter-check it, 'twas more great<note place="margin">Gauiſi ſunt gaud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o magno valde.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then text could well deſcribe, or I repeat.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like as a mother of a ſonne belou'd</l>
                  <l>As her eye ſight, from her eye-ſight remou'd</l>
                  <l>By a long abſence, and no newes arriuing,</l>
                  <l>Whether he doe conſort the dead or liuing,</l>
                  <l>Grieues at her hap, while heart-diſmaying feares</l>
                  <l>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt out her ſorrow, not in words, but teares;</l>
                  <l>Which when paſt hope ſhe ſees him home returne,</l>
                  <l>Ceaſt any longer his deceaſe to mourne,</l>
                  <l>And rauiſht in her ioy, her ſpirits drownd</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a deluge, falls into a ſwound:</l>
                  <l>But hauing once thoſe powers recollected,</l>
                  <l>Seeing the obiect by her ſo affected,</l>
                  <l>Kiſſes, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>braces, hugs her deareſt Boy,</l>
                  <l>Ready to skip out of her skin for ioy:</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:19248:22"/>
                  <l>So fared it with the Magi; when the Starre</l>
                  <l>Firſt diſappear'd, it made no doubt a warre</l>
                  <l>Within them, ſundry paſſions did conteſt,</l>
                  <l>But gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fe ſoone gets the maſtery of the reſt;</l>
                  <l>Yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ong the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rabbed tyrant doth not reigue,</l>
                  <l>Ere he be clean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> depos'd, the Starre againe</l>
                  <l>By new appearing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ters quite the ſtate;</l>
                  <l>So ioy ſucceeds, and doth pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dominate;</l>
                  <l>Tun'd to a holy key, their tongues doth ſound</l>
                  <l>Lauo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>taes, while their heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth dance a Round.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Star<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hether a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in that faſhion,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe ſome radiant holy inſpiration,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whether an errant P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et among the ſeuen,</l>
                  <l>Or one of thoſe faire bodies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ixt in heauen,</l>
                  <l>Sent downe to ſerue the turne or elſe created</l>
                  <l>For this ſole vſe, and then anihilated,</l>
                  <l>I will not ſtand to queſtion: on it went</l>
                  <l>As a ſure conuoy, for the courſe it hent</l>
                  <l>Was not orbicular, but ſo direct</l>
                  <l>As they could wiſh a guide, whoſe beſt reſpect</l>
                  <l>Might leade them on; the motion of it ſlow,</l>
                  <l>And as it may be well concluded, low,</l>
                  <l>Elſe could it not haue kept an equall pace,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet hauefully pointed to the place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come to the houſe, as if it had no will</l>
                  <l>For any further motion, it ſtood ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And ouer the poore cottage long did houer,</l>
                  <l>Or like ſome golden Canopie, did couer</l>
                  <l>The place of Chriſts abode: which once deſcride</l>
                  <l>By the wiſe men, its luſter it did hide,</l>
                  <l>And ne'er was ſeene againe, although ſome tell,</l>
                  <l>Gliding from thence, it fell into a Well.</l>
                  <l>Interpreters doe by this Starre expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Such as turne men to faith and righteouſneſſe.</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:19248:23"/>
                  <l>Thrice happy are thoſe Starre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, which ſoules do guid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>To Chriſt, and alſo there themſelues abide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Enter'd they find the Infant with his Mother;</l>
                  <l>She puts not out her Child vnto another:</l>
                  <l>Me thinkes it is an error againſt kind,</l>
                  <l>That Mothers which haue ſtore of milke aſſign'd,</l>
                  <l>Should dry thoſe fountaines, to preſerue their beauty,</l>
                  <l>From whence their infants ſhould ſuck loue and duty</l>
                  <l>Or that for ſtate, for trouble, or for pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>They ſhould expoſe ſuch an vnualew'd treaſure</l>
                  <l>As children are, vnto another, care,</l>
                  <l>While they themſelues thereof will beare no ſhare.</l>
                  <l>The bleſſed Virgin bare a better mind,</l>
                  <l>To her owne iſſue then to proue vnkind,</l>
                  <l>Milke ſhe a bleſſing knew, dry breaſts a curſe,</l>
                  <l>Therefore ſhe dain'd her ſelfe to be a nurſe:</l>
                  <l>The wiſe men when they come, the Infant ſee</l>
                  <l>Hang at her breaſts, or dandled on her knee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now did the Magi meet their full deſire,</l>
                  <l>And might with <hi>Simeon</hi> wiſh they might expire:</l>
                  <l>Great was their ioy, when they beheld the Starre.</l>
                  <l>To ſee the Sun muſt needs tranſcend it farre:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> reioyc'd to ſee Chriſts day in ſpirit;<note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 46.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Your ioy muſt needs be greater, which inherit</l>
                  <l>A larger bleſſing, you in fleſh behold him,</l>
                  <l>And haue that fauour in your armes to fold him:</l>
                  <l>Prophets and Kings haue long deſir'd in vaine,</l>
                  <l>To ſee what you ſee, <hi>Judahs</hi> Soueraigne;<note place="margin">Luk. 10. 24.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Therefore (to him who beſt can cenſure things)</l>
                  <l>Happier you are then Prophets, or then Kings.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet let me ſay, 'twas not the ſight alone</l>
                  <l>That made theſe wiſe men happy, had they gone</l>
                  <l>No further, they had ne'er arriu'd at bliſſe,</l>
                  <l>Many eyes ſaw him which of that ſhall miſſe:</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:19248:23"/>
                  <l>But theſe wiſe men when once they come before him,</l>
                  <l>Fall proſtrate on the ground, and doe adore him:</l>
                  <l>Well might good <hi>Bernard</hi> this ſtrange act admire,</l>
                  <l>That wiſe men, great men, who to ſenſe were higher</l>
                  <l>Then what they fell ſo low to, ſhould afford</l>
                  <l>Such worſhip to an Infant, poorely ſtord</l>
                  <l>With what ſhould fit a Royall birth, the place,</l>
                  <l>Attendants dreſſing, cradle had no grace</l>
                  <l>To moue ſuch vaſſalage; ſure God inſpir'd</l>
                  <l>(A thing which well deſerues to be admir'd)</l>
                  <l>Such Faith into their minds, as made them ſee</l>
                  <l>A God head clothed with humanity.</l>
                  <l>Being to come fore one of more command<note place="margin">Athanaſius.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then Perſiaes Monarke, with an empty hand</l>
                  <l>They dare not make approach, but ope their treaſure,</l>
                  <l>And giue their owne in an abundant meaſure:</l>
                  <l>The gifts they dedicate to Chriſt are three,<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To note they did adore the Trinitie:</l>
                  <l>Or elſe to ſhew, the perſon they ador'd,</l>
                  <l>Although but one, was with three Natures ſtor'd,</l>
                  <l>Deity, Soule and Body; or to bring</l>
                  <l>His threefold Office of Prieſt, Prophet, King,</l>
                  <l>To our remembrance; therefore ſome doe call</l>
                  <l>Theſe, ſacramentall gifts; Propheticall<note place="margin">Cyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tian. Rupertus. Baſfil.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Others entitle them; the firſt was Gold,</l>
                  <l>Which with a King doth correſpondence hold;</l>
                  <l>Or elſe they offer plenty of their Ore,</l>
                  <l>That to ſupply their wants they might haue ſtore</l>
                  <l>When Chriſt ſhould f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie to Egypt: they beſtow</l>
                  <l>Mirrhe, that a mortall man we might him know:</l>
                  <l>The Frankinſence they offer doth define,</l>
                  <l>As God he muſt haue ſacrifice Diuine.</l>
                  <l>Againe, pure Gold, cleare Mirrhe, ſweet Frankinſence,</l>
                  <l>Doe each of them afford a morall ſence;</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:19248:24"/>
                  <l>Gold ſignifies pure doctrine, Faith ſincere,</l>
                  <l>A charity refin'd, which God holds deare:</l>
                  <l>Myrrhe repreſents the teares of penitence</l>
                  <l>Shed for our ſinnes a mortified ſence</l>
                  <l>To worldly matters: Frankinſence doth ſhew</l>
                  <l>Perfum'd deuotion, where we muſt beſtow</l>
                  <l>The Incenſe of our prayers: theſe well preſented,</l>
                  <l>Are offerings wherewith God is much contented.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The wiſe men hauing their oblat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on ended,</l>
                  <l>And ſeene, and known what might be comprehended,</l>
                  <l>Take leaue, and doe betake them to their reſt,</l>
                  <l>Deeming themſelues to be not meanely bleſt</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a happy iſſue, now their mind</l>
                  <l>At quiet, a ſweet ſleepe their ſence doth bind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>About the dead time of the ſilent night,</l>
                  <l>They ſaw, or thought they ſaw a glorious light;</l>
                  <l>In it a ſhape more bright, an Angel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtood,</l>
                  <l>Who came from heauen to warne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their good,</l>
                  <l>And hauing gently wak'd them, with a voice</l>
                  <l>Able to charme attention, and reioyce</l>
                  <l>The very heart to heare it, thus he ſaid;</l>
                  <l>Let not your minds with terror be diſmaid,</l>
                  <l>Almighty God, whoſe I reioyce to be,</l>
                  <l>Hath ſent me to you on this embaſie:</l>
                  <l>The honour which you lately did his Sonne,</l>
                  <l>Hath ſo much fauour from his goodneſſe wonne,</l>
                  <l>That knowing you are bent to vndertake</l>
                  <l>A dangerous iourney, he deſires to make</l>
                  <l>The hazzard knowne vnto you: Iuda's King,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> I meane, is rather any thing,</l>
                  <l>Then wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he ſeem'd vnto you: his pretence</l>
                  <l>Of worſhip, when in that cloſe conference</l>
                  <l>He brake about the Infant, was a wile,</l>
                  <l>Both you and him the better to beguile;</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:19248:24"/>
                  <l>For in his heart he plotted long before,</l>
                  <l>To waſh his hands within the purple gore</l>
                  <l>Of his l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e blood, and choſe for this intent</l>
                  <l>Your ſimplen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe to be his inſtrument;</l>
                  <l>Meaning when he had ſeru'd his turne, to reaue</l>
                  <l>You of your deareſt liues, ſtriuing to leaue</l>
                  <l>A preſident vnto poſterity,</l>
                  <l>Of an vnmat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, vnheard of tyranny:</l>
                  <l>Be mindfull of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> words, and take good heed</l>
                  <l>How you returne to <hi>Herod,</hi> rather ſpeed</l>
                  <l>Into your Country b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſome other way,</l>
                  <l>For no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> danger waits vpon delay.</l>
                  <l>This ſaid, he quickly vaniſht out of ſight,</l>
                  <l>And they fell to their reſt that reſt of night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No ſooner did the grav-eyed Morne appeare,</l>
                  <l>And by her bluſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hew the Sunne was neare,</l>
                  <l>But to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ourney they themſelues addreſſe,</l>
                  <l>And mindfull of the viſion, which did preſſe</l>
                  <l>Their memories afreſh, they leaue the rode</l>
                  <l>Which leades to S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>em, though the tract were broad,</l>
                  <l>And ride through la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, and by-waies, till at laſt</l>
                  <l>The confines of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udea they are paſt.</l>
                  <l>Secure from danger, their poſt-haſte they ſtay,</l>
                  <l>And trauaile on at leaſure, by the way</l>
                  <l>Diſcourſing with ioy not to be expreſt,</l>
                  <l>How highly they were in that iourney bleſt:</l>
                  <l>Ere many daies their Country ſmoke appeares,</l>
                  <l>And they in peace at ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e liue many yeeres.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I cannot leaue this part of hiſtory,</l>
                  <l>Till I haue ſhewed a vſefull myſtery:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> by the vnanimous aſſent</l>
                  <l>Of Fathers, doth the diuell repreſent,</l>
                  <l>They then which by Gods mercy are ſet free</l>
                  <l>From bondage, worſe then Egypts ſlauery,</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:19248:25"/>
                  <l>Satans oppreſſion, muſt abhorre ſuch bands,</l>
                  <l>And take good heed they fall not in his hands.</l>
                  <l>The ſilly Bird hauing eſcap'd the net,</l>
                  <l>Farre from the fatall place herſelfe will get.</l>
                  <l>The Lambe which from the Wolfe hath got away,</l>
                  <l>Will no more venture from the flocke to ſtray.</l>
                  <l>If by the Goſpels Starre we once are brought</l>
                  <l>To Chriſt, let vs by no temptation wrought,</l>
                  <l>Turne backe to <hi>Herod;</hi> but forſaking quite</l>
                  <l>The workes of darkneſſe, in Gods Word delight.</l>
                  <l>Indeed I know we are to trauaile farre</l>
                  <l>To our owne Country, in this world we are<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 11.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But ſtrangers: he that liues the longeſt age,</l>
                  <l>Doth waſte his life in tedious pilgrimage:</l>
                  <l>Heauen is our happy home, and we muſt ſtriue,</l>
                  <l>Though cloſe by hell we paſſe, how to arriue</l>
                  <l>Vnto that bleſſed Harbor, by the way</l>
                  <l>Remouing all ſuch rubs as would vs ſtay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But let me tell you, leſt we chance to ſtray,</l>
                  <l>Our iourney thither lyes another way:</l>
                  <l>'Tis not the too-too common road of vice,</l>
                  <l>Which is the paſſage vnto Paradice;</l>
                  <l>Ah no, the path which vnto bliſſe doth lead<note place="margin">Matth. 7. 13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is ſtraight, and few they are that doe it tread:</l>
                  <l>Then, onely then, another way we take,<note place="margin">Immutatio viae emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datio vitae: Euſebius Emiſſenus. <hi>1. King. 13.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When of our vicious life a change we make.</l>
                  <l>Like as the Prophet which was ſent to cry</l>
                  <l>Againſt that Altar of impiety,</l>
                  <l>Set vp by <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> had command</l>
                  <l>Not to goe backe vnto his natiue Land</l>
                  <l>By the ſame way he came: the like haue we,</l>
                  <l>VVe muſt our old waies leaue, and ſpeedily</l>
                  <l>As we new creatures are, new wayes enquire,</l>
                  <l>Such as may bring vs whither we deſire.</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:19248:25"/>
                  <l>He that by ſinne hath left heauens vſuall track,</l>
                  <l>Muſt by repentance a new way come back.</l>
                  <l>Haſt thou walkt on in luſts impurity?</l>
                  <l>Returne another way, by chaſtety.</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou with pride a ſtately march maintaine?</l>
                  <l>Another way humility regaine.</l>
                  <l>In auarice didſt thou delight to moue?</l>
                  <l>Returne another way, and walke in loue.</l>
                  <l>Did ſharpe contention make thee trudge to Law?</l>
                  <l>From that miſleading path thy feet withdraw,</l>
                  <l>And ſtriue to liue in peace. Did thy heart range</l>
                  <l>In vſuries wilde maze? O let it change</l>
                  <l>(Though much againſt thy natiue conſtitution)</l>
                  <l>With good <hi>Zacheus</hi> to a reſtitution.</l>
                  <l>In fine if we wander from truth, or ſtray</l>
                  <l>Neuer ſo little from the narrow way,</l>
                  <l>We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſſe our path, and ſo abberring rome</l>
                  <l>From the right way, ſhould leade vs to our home.</l>
                  <l>And therefore as the trauailer in doubt</l>
                  <l>Which way to take, with heed doth looke about</l>
                  <l>To ſpie ſome houſe, or perſon, which may be</l>
                  <l>A helpe to him in his perplexitie,</l>
                  <l>And neuer leaue enquiring, till he know</l>
                  <l>Which way he muſt decline, and which way goe:</l>
                  <l>So if yee be in doubt which path to hold,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Salomons</hi> faire Spouſe get to the fold,</l>
                  <l>Where ſhepheards keepe their flock, of them enquire,<note place="margin">Cant. 1. 8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And they will ſatisfie your iuſt deſire;</l>
                  <l>Then hauing found it, keepe it with delight,</l>
                  <l>And neither turne to the left hand, nor right:</l>
                  <l>So ſhall ye find what euer may betide</l>
                  <l>In your way thither, 'twill you ſafely guide</l>
                  <l>To your owne Country, where you ſhall poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>More good then heart can thinke, or tongue expreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="Thursday" type="daily_meditation">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:19248:26"/>
               <head>Thurſdaies Meditation, or the fifth <hi>Canto.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>An Angell is to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſent,</l>
                     <l>To tell him <hi>Hérods</hi> foule intent:</l>
                     <l>He with his charge to Egypt flies,</l>
                     <l>And there remaines ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l <hi>Herod</hi> dies.</l>
                  </lg>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>NO ſooner had the Magi left the Land</l>
                  <l>Of Paleſtine, but He which hath command</l>
                  <l>Of all that know a beeing, and can ſee</l>
                  <l>Things plotted with the greateſt ſecrecy,</l>
                  <l>And eaſily elude them, di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> intend</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Herods</hi> proiect a vaine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fruitleſſe end:</l>
                  <l>God can (though man be crafty to deuiſe)</l>
                  <l>Infatuate the Counſels of the wiſe,</l>
                  <l>And free his children from what may annoy them,</l>
                  <l>Though malice ioyne with cunning to deſtroy them</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who from Iſrael will not part,</l>
                  <l>Wants of his will, yet for it feeles the ſmart:<note place="margin">Conſilium diuinum dum deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletur, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia dum reluctat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur. Greg.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>So <hi>Saul,</hi> who practiz'd <hi>Dauid</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> confound,</l>
                  <l>Did himſelfe fall, and <hi>Jſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> ſonne was croun'd:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Herod</hi> who did ſeeke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> haue depriu'd</l>
                  <l>Chriſt of his life, did find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imſelfe ſhort liu'd.</l>
                  <l>Thus Gods decree while hund, doth take effect,</l>
                  <l>And humane wiſedome w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ile it ſtriues, is checkt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now were all humane eyes ſhut vp in ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>But ſuch whom care, or paine did open keepe,</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:19248:26"/>
                  <l>When a bleſt Angell (Angels are prepar'd</l>
                  <l>To be to Gods Elect a ſurer guard</l>
                  <l>Then mortals can be) vnto <hi>Ioſeph</hi> came,</l>
                  <l>Sent to that iuſt man in <hi>Iehouahs</hi> Name,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Sun-like preſence had ſo bright aray,</l>
                  <l>That it made mid-night to excell mid-day:</l>
                  <l>Yet the good man feareleſſe, becauſe vntainted,</l>
                  <l>And with ſuch apparitions pre-acquainted,</l>
                  <l>Expected the euent; when thus made bold,</l>
                  <l>The Angell did his Embaſy vnfold:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O thou which from the Lord ſuch grace haſt won,</l>
                  <l>To be the Foſter-father of his Sonne,</l>
                  <l>And husband (though thou liueſt more like a brother)</l>
                  <l>Vnto that euer bleſſed Virgin Mother,</l>
                  <l>Looke well vnto thy charge, the Wolfe doth warch</l>
                  <l>With bloody mind, both Lamb and Eue to catch,</l>
                  <l>That he may prey vpon them, therefore take</l>
                  <l>The tender Infant, and his Mother make</l>
                  <l>Co-partner in thy flight, to Egypt flee,</l>
                  <l>There's roome and ſafety for thy Charge and Thee:</l>
                  <l>There plant thy habitation, and remaine,</l>
                  <l>Till thou mayſt ſafely venture backe againe,</l>
                  <l>Which ſafety when the time ſhall once afford,</l>
                  <l>Ile be a Meſſenger to bring thee word.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This meſſage ended, backe the Angell goes,</l>
                  <l>When preſently good <hi>Joſeph</hi> doth diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe to Gods command, that very night</l>
                  <l>With his deare charge he 'gins to take his flight.</l>
                  <l>But though ſuch haſte <hi>Ioſeph</hi> made to be gone,</l>
                  <l>Wee'll ſtay a while, and meditate hereon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That woman in the vncouth Wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">Reuel. 12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom neere her time the Dragon did diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>One thinkes, doth repreſent the Church; another</l>
                  <l>(Not much amiſſe) the bleſſed Virgin Mother:</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:19248:27"/>
                  <l>Indeed the Dragon ſuits with <hi>Herod</hi> well,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Mary</hi> is the womans paralell:</l>
                  <l>The ſtory tells vs, that the woman fled</l>
                  <l>The Dragons furie, when deliuered:</l>
                  <l>So was the bleſſed Virgin glad to flie</l>
                  <l>With her young Babe from <hi>Herods</hi> cruelty:</l>
                  <l>The Dragon there ſtood ready to deuoure</l>
                  <l>The Child, when he was borne; and euery houre</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> did gape for newes, that he might ſlay</l>
                  <l>The bleſſedſt Infant euer yet ſaw day:</l>
                  <l>Yet Child and Mother both eſcaped there:</l>
                  <l>So Chriſt and <hi>Mary</hi> both preſerued were:</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Moſes</hi> guarded by Gods mighty hand,</l>
                  <l>Came ſafely of from the vniuſt command</l>
                  <l>Of perſecuting <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and became</l>
                  <l>A mighty Captaine in <hi>Iehouahs</hi> Name</l>
                  <l>To quell the pride of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and ſet free</l>
                  <l>The Hebrewes from Egyptian ſlauery:</l>
                  <l>So by Gods prouidence did Chriſt eſcape</l>
                  <l>From Dragon <hi>Herods</hi> mouth which wide did gape,</l>
                  <l>To ſwallow him aliue, that he might be</l>
                  <l>Vnto his people in captiuity</l>
                  <l>A mighty leader, and the power quell</l>
                  <l>Of Sinne, and Sathan, of the Graue, and Hell,</l>
                  <l>And ſo in fine his Iſrael ſafely bring</l>
                  <l>From bondage worſe then vnder Egypts King:</l>
                  <l>Finally when the Dragon did perceiue</l>
                  <l>Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> force againſt the woman vaine, did leaue</l>
                  <l>To perſecute her, yet did i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly burne</l>
                  <l>In indignation, and his fury t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne</l>
                  <l>To warre vpon the remnant of her ſeed,</l>
                  <l>Hoping to meet ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with ſuccesfull ſpeed:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Herod</hi> fruſtrated of his deſire,</l>
                  <l>Suffers his heart to burne in flaming fire</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:19248:27"/>
                  <l>Of furious rage, and will needes wreake his ſpleene</l>
                  <l>On ſilly infants, but this ſhalbe ſeene</l>
                  <l>More largely, in the progreſſe of this ſtory,</l>
                  <l>Chriſts flight a while keeps back the Infants glory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like as a gardner when he ſpies a plant,</l>
                  <l>Full of faire hope fit elbow roome to want,</l>
                  <l>As nigh ſome ouerſpreading tree, bereauen</l>
                  <l>Of the Suns heat, and the fat dew of heauen,</l>
                  <l>With care remoues it to another place,</l>
                  <l>Where it thriues mainly, in a little ſpace:</l>
                  <l>So when the Lord his Sonne that plant did ſee</l>
                  <l>Plac'd to neare <hi>Herod</hi> that farre ſpreading tree,</l>
                  <l>Yet fruitleſſe, therefore worthy to be feld</l>
                  <l>Leſt the vnholſome ſhadow death ſhould peld</l>
                  <l>To the neare neighbouring plant, his powerfull hand</l>
                  <l>Doth now tranſplant him to another land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that in flight our refuge is heere flies,</l>
                  <l>He that aſſiſts vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gainſt our enemies,</l>
                  <l>Auoids the furie of his mortall foes,</l>
                  <l>And like an exile into Egypt goes:</l>
                  <l>That in ſuch kind of dire calamities</l>
                  <l>He might with vs the better ſympathize:</l>
                  <l>Our Sauiour Chriſt without a Gyges ring</l>
                  <l>Could haue obſcur'd his perſon from the King.</l>
                  <l>Or had he pleaſ'd what euer was intended</l>
                  <l>Gainſt <hi>Herods</hi> malice haue himſelfe defended:</l>
                  <l>He that by fire did his <hi>Eliah</hi> guard</l>
                  <l>He that an hoſt of Angels had prepar'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eliſha</hi> to ſecure, he that did ſaue</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Daniel</hi> from Lyons, <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the graue,</l>
                  <l>Had it ſeem'd good could heere haue gon as farre</l>
                  <l>And quail'd the force of <hi>Herods</hi> men of warre:</l>
                  <l>But he choſe rather to ſepoſe his might,</l>
                  <l>And to expoſe his perſon vnto flight:</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:19248:28"/>
                  <l>Either to ſhew what he himſelfe doth ſay,</l>
                  <l>He came no worldly Scepter here to ſway:<note place="margin">Ioh. 18.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or elſe by his example to declare,</l>
                  <l>The Church for perſecution muſt prepare:</l>
                  <l>Or it may be to teach vs, that the Lord</l>
                  <l>No extraordinary will afford,</l>
                  <l>When we haue ordinary meanes at hand,</l>
                  <l>By which we may withdraw, and quit the Land,</l>
                  <l>To worke our ſafety: or to teach in fine</l>
                  <l>Vs perſonall perſecution to decline:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Moſes</hi> fled from <hi>Pharaohs</hi> cruelty:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Dauid</hi> from his ſonnes impiety:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Paul,</hi> no ſafety being in the Towne,</l>
                  <l>Was in a basket by the wall let downe,</l>
                  <l>That he might ſcape the danger; ſo againe</l>
                  <l>He fled from Salem, fearing to be ſlaine:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Polycarpe</hi> in perſecutions heat,</l>
                  <l>Did by aduice, for a while change his ſeate:<note place="margin">Euſebius.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>So <hi>Athanaſius</hi> did often flie</l>
                  <l>From that blood thirſting Arrian tyranny:</l>
                  <l>So when <hi>Iuſtina, Valentimans</hi> Mother,<note place="margin">Socrates ſcholaſlicus.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her rage againſt S <hi>Ambroſe</hi> could not ſmother,</l>
                  <l>He fled from Millaine: <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> like fate</l>
                  <l>Drew from Bizantium, to ſhun the hate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>xia</hi> bare vnto him: Chriſt our Sauiour,</l>
                  <l>When paſt an Infant, had the like behauiour:</l>
                  <l>So when the Phariſes a counſell tooke</l>
                  <l>Againſt his life, their preſence he forſooke:<note place="margin">Mat. 12. 15. Luk. 4. Iohn. 8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>So when the Nazarens malicious will</l>
                  <l>Would throw him headlong from the City hill,</l>
                  <l>He left the place: ſo when with fell deſpite</l>
                  <l>The Iewes did ſeeke to ſtone him, from their ſight</l>
                  <l>He hid himſelfe: to make this truth more plaine,</l>
                  <l>He giues this as a precept, to remaine</l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:19248:28"/>
                  <l>To all ſucceeding times, when tyrants hate,</l>
                  <l>Shall rather ſeeke your liues, then your eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Out of one City to another flie,<note place="margin">Mat. 10. 23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſaue your ſelues from their ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rne cruelty:</l>
                  <l>This is to be like cunning Serpents wiſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 10. 16.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When innocence of Doues will not ſuffice.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But we muſt know our Sauiour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>led not death,<note place="margin">Mortem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulit non fugit: Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt:</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Out of a feare to leeſe his vicall breath:</l>
                  <l>Onely for this cauſe he did now foreſlow it,</l>
                  <l>That afterwards he better might beſtow it:</l>
                  <l>He meant to lay it downe, as a rare gift</l>
                  <l>Of his owne bounty, not by <hi>Herods</hi> drift,</l>
                  <l>By his freewill he did intend to die,<note place="margin">Morietur non vinculo neceſſitatis, ſed propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis: Fulgen.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And not out of a fore'd neceſſity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſeeing thou wouldſt haue thy Sonne, O Lord,</l>
                  <l>To flie, wherefore to Egypt ſo abhord?</l>
                  <l>Can that to thy belou'd ſafe harbor giue,</l>
                  <l>In which thy Iſrael did in bondage liue.</l>
                  <l>Haue the Egyptians thoſe plagues forgot</l>
                  <l>Thou didſt impoſe vpon them? Will they not</l>
                  <l>Study reuenge? Or may not <hi>Ioſeph</hi> feare,</l>
                  <l>If Egypts King of his arriuall heare,</l>
                  <l>He ſhall be taken for an Hebrew Spie,</l>
                  <l>And by ſome vncouth torment forc'd to die.</l>
                  <l>O let not fleſh and blood expoſtulate</l>
                  <l>With Gods determination, or debate</l>
                  <l>The matter any further, God who drawes</l>
                  <l>Honey from He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lock with the Bee, can cauſe</l>
                  <l>Each place that is to ſerue vnto his will,</l>
                  <l>And ſafety raiſe euen from thoſe would kill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The time was once when his almighty Hand</l>
                  <l>Threw plagues apace on the Egyptian Land,</l>
                  <l>The worſt of which wherewith they were annoi'd</l>
                  <l>Was, when their firſt borne iſſue was deſtroi'd;</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:19248:29"/>
                  <l>To recompence this loſſe he ſends his owne</l>
                  <l>And by his bounty his great loue makes knowne.</l>
                  <l>Once making <hi>Moſes</hi> his fit inſtrument,<note place="margin">Exod. 10.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cymmerian darkneſſe on their Land he ſent.</l>
                  <l>And which was worſe, groping for light as blind</l>
                  <l>Suffred them liue in darkneſſe of their mind.</l>
                  <l>Therfore his ſonne, that Sun ſhall now ariſe</l>
                  <l>To giue them light, which doe not ſhut their eyes</l>
                  <l>Againſt his ſplendour, for as ſtories tell,</l>
                  <l>When he came thither all their Idolls fell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And as we read that <hi>Joſeph</hi> beſt belou'd</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Iacob,</hi> from his Fathers eye remou'd</l>
                  <l>By enuie of his bretheren, was conuayed</l>
                  <l>To Egypt where by Gods direction ſtay'd;</l>
                  <l>He was a kind of Sauiour to the land,</l>
                  <l>In keeping famine out which did command</l>
                  <l>After a ſeuen yeares plenty: ſo more want</l>
                  <l>Threatning to ruine Egypt which grew ſcant</l>
                  <l>Of grace and goodneſſe, Chriſt a Sauiour came,</l>
                  <l>And in great mercy did preſerue the ſame.</l>
                  <l>For he the true bread is where he doth dwell</l>
                  <l>All fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine from the ſoule he doth expell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By this time <hi>Ioſeph</hi> whom much care did preſſe,</l>
                  <l>Had gotten all thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in a readineſſe,</l>
                  <l>And in the couert of the ſhady night</l>
                  <l>Begins his iourney, darkneſſe could not fright<note place="margin">Non atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit verus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediens qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſit quod praecipitur: hoc ſolo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentus quia pracipitur. Bernard.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Him or his charge: obedience doth contend</l>
                  <l>How to pleaſe God although it ſenſe offend.</l>
                  <l>Not into what commanded is, it pries,</l>
                  <l>But that it is commanded doth ſuffice:</l>
                  <l>Good <hi>Ioſeph</hi> murmures not at the great paine</l>
                  <l>Or the long iourney he muſt entertaine,</l>
                  <l>He ſtaggers not in faith, that he doth flie</l>
                  <l>Which muſt ſaue others from their miſery:</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19248:29"/>
                  <l>But as he came from Abraham, behaues</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe like <hi>Abraham,</hi> in his mind he graues</l>
                  <l>How ready the glad father was to goe</l>
                  <l>When God commanded, and ſhould I be ſlow,</l>
                  <l>To execute ſaid he what God enioynes,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould want worth, to iſſue from ſuch loynes</l>
                  <l>Mans heart muſt be like paper, cleane, and white,</l>
                  <l>Wheron the Lord what he ſhall pleaſe may write:</l>
                  <l>Or like to waxe well ſuppled by the hand,</l>
                  <l>Be ſoft and pliant to his iuſt command</l>
                  <l>We muſt in all things, ſeeme they good or ill,</l>
                  <l>Conforme our wiſhes to out ſoueraignes will:</l>
                  <l>Faith and obedience ſtand not to diſpute,</l>
                  <l>But are ſtill ready preſt to execute:</l>
                  <l>Our God, obedience doth ſo highly prize,</l>
                  <l>That he prefers it before ſacrifice.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And worthily, fot they who with conſent</l>
                  <l>A legall ſacrifice to God preſent,</l>
                  <l>But other fleſh, the fleſh of beaſts doe till,<note place="margin">In victimis allena caro obedientia vero volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas propria mactatur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Greg.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where we obeying ſacrifice our will.</l>
                  <l>Thus did good <hi>Joſeph,</hi> whom no let could ſtay</l>
                  <l>No not ſo long as for the lightſome day:</l>
                  <l>And well in the black night did they begin</l>
                  <l>Their trauaile from a place more black in ſinne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now gan the day from out the eaſt appeare,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe comfortable light their hearts did cheare,</l>
                  <l>And ere the Sun had fully ſhone an hower</l>
                  <l>They found themſelues got ſafe from <hi>Herods</hi> power:</l>
                  <l>At length in Egypt they arriue what towne</l>
                  <l>Did giue them harbour, the text ſets not downe</l>
                  <l>Nor will I ſeeke to know, there they remaine,</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Herods</hi> death did call them back againe.</l>
                  <l>All this ſaith the Euangeliſt was done,</l>
                  <l>To firme that prophecie which ſaid, My Sonne</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:19248:30"/>
                  <l>From Egypt haue I call'd: the literall ſence</l>
                  <l>I know, concerneth Iſrael, who from thence</l>
                  <l>Was brought by mighty hand, yet hath reſpect</l>
                  <l>To Chriſt, as types doe vpon truths reflect:</l>
                  <l>And as Gods people, Iſrael, did ſtay</l>
                  <l>A time in Egypt, till the Lord made way</l>
                  <l>For their departure; ſo his bleſſed Sonne</l>
                  <l>Had for a while his habitation</l>
                  <l>In the ſame Egypt, till the Lord did call him,</l>
                  <l>Whom there I leaue to that which did befall him.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="Friday" type="daily_meditation">
               <head>Fridaies Meditation, or the ſixth <hi>Canto.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Kings fierce rage, his men of warre</l>
                     <l>The innocents doe maſſacre:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rachel</hi> doth mourne her heauy loſſe,</l>
                     <l>And will no comfort in her croſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>TIme now (which erſt did vnto <hi>Iudabs</hi> King</l>
                  <l>Seeme to moue forward with a lazy wing)</l>
                  <l>Made him ſuſpect, or rather plainely ſee</l>
                  <l>The wiſe men did delude his ſubtilty:</l>
                  <l>And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re was reaſon for it, he that thought</l>
                  <l>To mocke, is mockt, and rakes but what he brought;</l>
                  <l>The law of taliation did require</l>
                  <l>He ſhould meet this euent: the ſitteſt hire<note place="margin">Nequc enim lex luſtior vila: Ouid.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>For fraud is ſlic deceit, and they that cheriſh</l>
                  <l>Diſſembling, in their art doe iuſtly periſh:</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:19248:30"/>
                  <l>God on theſe men his iudgements doth expreſſe,<note place="margin">Iob 5. 13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And takes the wiſe in their owne craftineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now this deluſion in the King begets</l>
                  <l>An indignation, and in rage him ſets.</l>
                  <l>When Tyrants cannot by their craft preuaile,</l>
                  <l>In a red Sea of cruelty they ſaile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But why, O <hi>Herod,</hi> wert thou thus perplext?</l>
                  <l>Why doeſt thou rage? or wherefore art thou vext?</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou not know that Chriſts birth was diuine?</l>
                  <l>Or wert thou blind, becauſe the Sunne did ſhine?</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou not conuocate from euery Tribe</l>
                  <l>Many chiefe Prieſts, many a learned Scribe?</l>
                  <l>And did not they by ancient Prophecy</l>
                  <l>Reſolue the truth of this deepe myſtery?</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou not know the wiſe men came thus farre</l>
                  <l>To worſhip Chriſt. led by a glorious Starre?</l>
                  <l>Thy cheeke ſhould rather bluſh, then thy heart flame,</l>
                  <l>And looke red, not with anger, but with ſhame,</l>
                  <l>That ſuch Barbarians, which were farre below thee,</l>
                  <l>Should in their zeale to God ſo much outgoe thee:</l>
                  <l>The loue and faith wherewith they were inſpir'd</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhouldſt haue imitated, and admir'd:</l>
                  <l>For vnleſſe thou didſt altogether ſhun</l>
                  <l>Prophetique truth, ſo much it might haue won</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy iudgement, that by iuſt compare</l>
                  <l>Of paſſed things with ſuch as preſent are,</l>
                  <l>Thou mightſt conclude, this was' not a deluſion</l>
                  <l>Of the wiſe men, but a confuſion,</l>
                  <l>Which God, who ſometimes counterchecks a King,</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy wicked purpoſe meant to bring.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſay thou hadſt ſome iniury receiu'd,</l>
                  <l>And by the cunning Magi wert deceiu'd,</l>
                  <l>How had the ſilly Innocents offended,</l>
                  <l>That ſo much miſciefe is 'gainſt them intended:</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:19248:31"/>
                  <l>O why is their vniuſt deſtruction ſought?</l>
                  <l>which nere ſo much as wrong'd thee in a thought,</l>
                  <l>Surely, ſhould Iordan lend thee all her ſtore,</l>
                  <l>It could not waſh away the purple gore</l>
                  <l>That hangs vpon thee, with thee ſtill ſhall bide</l>
                  <l>The title of a bloudy Homicide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou ſought'ſt for Chriſt, but went'ſt too far about,</l>
                  <l>Tis faith, not furie, which muſt finde him out;</l>
                  <l>O fooliſh <hi>Herod</hi> which doſt thinke t' expell</l>
                  <l>Him that will ſtill be King of Iſraell,</l>
                  <l>Yea King of Heauen and Earth, in ſpite of thee</l>
                  <l>Out of thy poore, and petty liberty:</l>
                  <l>O wicked <hi>Herod,</hi> and of lewd behauiour</l>
                  <l>Who fearing thy ſucceſſor, hat'ſt thy Sauiour:</l>
                  <l>O bloudy <hi>Herod,</hi> which by the fell death</l>
                  <l>Of harmeleſſe children, wouldſt prolo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, thy breath:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But little admiration it requires,</l>
                  <l>That Tyrants ſeeke to compaſſe their deſires,</l>
                  <l>Or found their thrones on ſlaughtered innocence,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pharaoh</hi> long ſince had taught him to diſpence</l>
                  <l>With murders of that ranke, who to ſecure</l>
                  <l>His crowne, made <hi>Abrahams</hi> yſſue to endure</l>
                  <l>A heauy burden, while he did command</l>
                  <l>To drowne their yſſue male throughout the land.<note place="margin">Exod. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>So did <hi>Abimelec</hi> the baſe borne ſonne</l>
                  <l>Of that couragious warriour, <hi>Gedeon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who through the bloud of 70. brothers waded,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Crowne moſt wrongfully inuaded,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> was more vnnaturall then theſe,</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt his owne ſonne he could not rage appeaſe,</l>
                  <l>But fearing he ſhould the Meſſias be,</l>
                  <l>Among the reſt he wrought his tragedy:</l>
                  <l>Therefore <hi>Auguſtus</hi> did this ſaying vſe,</l>
                  <l>If I were bound to liue among the Iewes,</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:19248:31"/>
                  <l>With greater willingneſſe I would be ſwine</l>
                  <l>Then ſonne to <hi>Herod:</hi> for by law deuine<note place="margin">Malo Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis porcum quam filium eſſe: <hi>Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Swines fleſh forbid the Hebrewes they did giue</l>
                  <l>A kinde of priuiledge the beaſts might liue,</l>
                  <l>Whereas King <hi>Herod</hi> a worſe beaſt did grutch</l>
                  <l>Vnto his owne childe to afford ſo much.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Lyon will not tender Infants ſlay,</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe meere hunger force him to ſuch prey,</l>
                  <l>O With what hunger then was <hi>Herod</hi> wag'd,</l>
                  <l>When he againſt ſo many Infants rag'd,</l>
                  <l>With hunger of ambition, which of all</l>
                  <l>The greateſt hunger we may iuſtly call:</l>
                  <l>Hunger of raigning ſure muſt needes be great,</l>
                  <l>Which to appeaſe it, muſt haue ſo much meate;</l>
                  <l>So many Infants fleſh, that thirſt is ſore</l>
                  <l>Which nought can ſatisfie but crimſin gore,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Enioy bloud thirſting <hi>Herod,</hi> re-inioy</l>
                  <l>Thy kingdome ſafely, free from all annoy,</l>
                  <l>He that aboue doth Heauenly crownes beſtow,</l>
                  <l>Gapes not for earthly ſcepters here belowe,</l>
                  <l>Such earth-bred honor Chriſt doth much deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>Elephants take no mice, nor Eagles flies:</l>
                  <l>Though he of power be for to caſt thee downe,</l>
                  <l>Yet feare no depriuation of thy crowne,</l>
                  <l>For though two Kings can in one kingdome raigne,</l>
                  <l>No more, then Heauen can two bright Suns ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l>Yet euery King may with him, in him daigne</l>
                  <l>His kingly Lord, his true Meſſias raigne,</l>
                  <l>As the faire Heauen with many Starres is dight,</l>
                  <l>And with the Sun, from whom they take their light:</l>
                  <l>Only learne mercy from this potent one,</l>
                  <l>And heape not bloud ſo long vpon thy Throne,</l>
                  <l>Till it become ſo ſlippery, as to threat</l>
                  <l>Each ſtep thou tak'ſt, to caſt thee from thy ſeat.</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:19248:32"/>
                  <l>But rage, like to the belly, hath no eares,</l>
                  <l>To reaſon deafe, it onely paſſion heares,</l>
                  <l>Aduice is vaine, ſay what I can or will,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> will be himſelfe, a tyrant ſtill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They ſay, that Bee who of the reſt is King,</l>
                  <l>Either hath none, or doth not vſe a ſting:</l>
                  <l>Surely this man, whom wretched Bethlehem ſees</l>
                  <l>Reeke in the blood of Infants, not of Bees,</l>
                  <l>But Waſpes was King, for waſplike full of ſpleene,<note place="margin">2. King. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>He thruſts his poyſonous ſting (ſo great his teene)</l>
                  <l>Into the fleſh of children, and doth kill</l>
                  <l>Thoſe, who to hurt him had nor power, nor will.</l>
                  <l>Indeed two Beares did certaine children ſley,</l>
                  <l>But cauſe they mockt Gods Prophet: thou then they</l>
                  <l>More fierce deſtroyſt the guiltleſſe: fearefull man,</l>
                  <l>Do'ſt thou dread ſilly childrens force? or can</l>
                  <l>Faint cowardize with thee preuaile ſo farre,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhouldſt gainſt Infants wage ſuch bloody warre.</l>
                  <l>Great praiſe no doubt, and many a worthy ſpoile</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt enioy, by giuing them the foile.</l>
                  <l>The noble Elephants will not inuade</l>
                  <l>The weaker ſort of beaſts: thou ſhakſt thy blade</l>
                  <l>At ſucking children, and ſendſt men of might,</l>
                  <l>To challenge thoſe that know not how to ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There is a ſtory of great <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How true, the Authors credit, and not mine,</l>
                  <l>Muſt anſwer: but the matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le relate,</l>
                  <l>And leaue the queſtion further to debate:</l>
                  <l>Before he came to Chriſtianity,</l>
                  <l>The Prince was troubled with a Leproſie;</l>
                  <l>To cure this ſickneſſe the aduice and care</l>
                  <l>Of his Phiſicians would haue him prepare</l>
                  <l>A Bath of Infants blood: ſure here the Diuill</l>
                  <l>Prompted his Doctors to ſo great an euill:</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:19248:32"/>
                  <l>But being by Gods prouidence conuerted,</l>
                  <l>He from ſo foule a ſlaughter was diuerted</l>
                  <l>By ſoules Phiſicians, who doe well aſſure him,</l>
                  <l>Baptiſme a Bath more powerfull is to cure him.</l>
                  <l>He hearkens to them, is baptiz'd, and free</l>
                  <l>Both from the bodies, and ſoules leproſie.</l>
                  <l>Behold, ambition <hi>Herods</hi> ſoule inuades,</l>
                  <l>Like a foule Leproſie; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atan perſwades</l>
                  <l>(Such is hells phiſicke) naught will doe him good,</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe he bathe himſelfe in Infants blood;</l>
                  <l>And not the opening of a ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e or two,</l>
                  <l>No, but their life blood this great cure muſt doe:</l>
                  <l>Therefore to ſatisfie the ſoule-ſicke King,</l>
                  <l>Each tender Babe muſt empty all his Spring;</l>
                  <l>And now God lets the Wolfe the Lambes deuoure,</l>
                  <l>Without reſtraining of his rage, or power,</l>
                  <l>He puts no bridle into <hi>Herods</hi> noſe,</l>
                  <l>But lets him take full ſwinge in his diſpoſe,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he knew how to draw good from ill,</l>
                  <l>And make this wicked action ſerue his will:</l>
                  <l>From Lyons mouth ſweet honey he can take,</l>
                  <l>And Marahs bitter waters wholeſome make.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> in this his rage doth type out thoſe</l>
                  <l>Of the malignant Church, who ſtill are foes</l>
                  <l>To the Church Militant, and by their will</l>
                  <l>Religion in it infant age would kill:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> like malice, and impiety,</l>
                  <l>Egyptian, Babylonian cruelty.</l>
                  <l>It is (though tyrants hold theſe termes in ſcorne)</l>
                  <l>To ſmother piety as ſoone as borne,</l>
                  <l>To quench Religion while it is a ſparke,</l>
                  <l>And drowne poore ſoules by keeping from the Arke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Againe, in <hi>Herods</hi> foule deſigne of blood,</l>
                  <l>Satans condition may be vnderſtood,</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:19248:33"/>
                  <l>Who ſeekes not only by malicious will,</l>
                  <l>Chriſt while an Infant in our heart to kill,</l>
                  <l>But many children more, euery good thought,</l>
                  <l>Though it be neuer into action brought,</l>
                  <l>To make thoſe babes good motions in vs die,</l>
                  <l>Though they want ſtrength to goe in act, and lie</l>
                  <l>In meditations cradle, is his glory,</l>
                  <l>But I leaue types to proſecute the ſtory:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>While <hi>Herod</hi> inly vext, became thus wilde,</l>
                  <l>With furious rage, the Deuill rockt his childe,</l>
                  <l>But would not let him ſleepe: like ſome mad beaſt,</l>
                  <l>By nature feirce, if wounded will not reſt,</l>
                  <l>But doubling his fell fury and euen blinde</l>
                  <l>With rage, regards no longer how to finde</l>
                  <l>His foe that hurt him, but with head and feete</l>
                  <l>Fiercely aſſailes the next that he doth meete:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Herod,</hi> who conceiu'd himſelfe much wrong'd</l>
                  <l>By the wiſe men, for whoſe returne he long'd,</l>
                  <l>His hope deluded like one robd of ſence</l>
                  <l>Wreakes his reuengefull ſpleene on Innocence:</l>
                  <l>For full of doubtfull thoughts as well as ſinnes,</l>
                  <l>To reaſon with himſelfe he thus begins:</l>
                  <l>What childe is this? that hath from Heauen his birth</l>
                  <l>Foretold, ere it be perfected on earth:</l>
                  <l>Vnto the World himſelfe he hath not ſhowne,</l>
                  <l>Yet is to thoſe that neuer ſaw him knowne:</l>
                  <l>Ouer no people yet he hath command,</l>
                  <l>And wiſe men, great men, leaue their natiue land</l>
                  <l>To waite vpon him: o who is the wight</l>
                  <l>That ouercomes me, and yet does not fight:</l>
                  <l>That like a tyrant ouer me doth raigne,</l>
                  <l>Ere he the kingdome (I poſſeſſe) obtaine:</l>
                  <l>If he already me of ſtate beguile,</l>
                  <l>What will he doe if he encreaſe a while?</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:19248:33"/>
                  <l>Poore as he is, he is more fear'd, then I</l>
                  <l>With all my riches, and authority:</l>
                  <l>Or elſe theſe wiſe men or impoſtors rather,</l>
                  <l>(For by their dealing leſſe I cannot gather)</l>
                  <l>Whom my intelligence is I did make,</l>
                  <l>Would not haue faltered with me for his ſake,</l>
                  <l>But here I vow, who euer doe be friend him</l>
                  <l>Nor heauen, nor hel ſhall from my power defend him:</l>
                  <l>No I will make (if my vnhappy fate</l>
                  <l>Croſſe not my will) Bethlem as deſolate</l>
                  <l>Of Infants, as this Infant hath made me</l>
                  <l>Of comfort, ſince his new nan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d ſoueraignty.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus he reſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s in rage, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> what that ſtill</l>
                  <l>To raſh attempts a Counſellor full ill,</l>
                  <l>Suggeſts vnto him, he in action brings,</l>
                  <l>So ſoone men execute the will of Kings:</l>
                  <l>And now come other actors on the ſtage,</l>
                  <l>The blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dy inſtruments of <hi>Herod</hi> rage</l>
                  <l>Made ready to preſent vnto our eye</l>
                  <l>A tragicke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceane of horrid cruelty.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not to examine who they were, we ſee</l>
                  <l>Subiect and King full well, and ill agree,</l>
                  <l>Tyrants doe neuer want fit Inſtruments,</l>
                  <l>To execute their very worſt intents:</l>
                  <l>Would wicked <hi>Saul</hi> haue the Lords Prieſts be ſlaine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Doeg</hi> the motion ſoone will entertaine:</l>
                  <l>Doth <hi>Dauid</hi> plot to ſtop <hi>Vr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ahs</hi> breath?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Joab</hi> will ſet him in the face of death:</l>
                  <l>Doth <hi>Iezabell</hi> 'gainſt <hi>Naboths</hi> life conſpire?</l>
                  <l>The elders will effect her lewde deſire:</l>
                  <l>The world yet neuer knew a Prince ſo vicious,</l>
                  <l>But that he ſhould haue men to be officious,</l>
                  <l>Such as account it an eſpeciall grace</l>
                  <l>To doe their Lords will be it nere ſo baſe:</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:19248:34"/>
                  <l>The officers of <hi>Herod</hi> bare this mind,</l>
                  <l>Ready to goe when he their warrant ſign'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And now ſuppoſe them vnto Bethlehem come,</l>
                  <l>Ready to act the tyrants fatall doome,</l>
                  <l>While the Sunne hides his head at ſuch a ſight,</l>
                  <l>As if a Noone he meant to make it night,</l>
                  <l>And with blacke clouds did couer his ſad face,</l>
                  <l>Grieuing that men ſhould haue ſo little grace:</l>
                  <l>The melting heauens doe alſo ſhowre downe raine,</l>
                  <l>As if they wept for the poore Infants paine;</l>
                  <l>Euen the walles there in a cold dew ſtood,</l>
                  <l>As ſtruck with horror, to ſee ſo much blood:</l>
                  <l>Yet theſe feele no remorce, nor once deſiſt</l>
                  <l>From the commanded murther, but perſiſt</l>
                  <l>In that abhorred worke of cruelty,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall them brand with laſting infamy:</l>
                  <l>With their ſwords drawne, that none this courſe may ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Into mens houſes they do force their way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here they an Infant from the cradle ſnatch,</l>
                  <l>There from the fathers armes another catch,</l>
                  <l>And the poore childrens ſad deſtruction wrought,</l>
                  <l>Ere the amazed parents had a thought</l>
                  <l>Of any danger neere: ſome they tranſpierce</l>
                  <l>With their blood thirſting ſword, others in fierce</l>
                  <l>And ſauage manner, they deuide aſunder,</l>
                  <l>While they that own them ſtand ſtone ſtill in wonder:</l>
                  <l>Me thinkes in one place I ſome father heare</l>
                  <l>(At his deare Infants danger ſtruck with feare)</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Niſus</hi> in the Poet, or more milde,</l>
                  <l>Crie out vnto the Butcher of his childe;</l>
                  <l>O ſpare my ſonne! or if you blood muſt ſpill,</l>
                  <l>Here turne your ſwords, the grieued father kill?</l>
                  <l>I might, he durſt not could not entertaine</l>
                  <l>A thought of wrong vnto his So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eraigne.</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:19248:34"/>
                  <l>Me thinkes I in another place behold</l>
                  <l>An Infant ſtab'd, whoſe pretty armes lay hold</l>
                  <l>About his mothers breaſt, whence he doth draine</l>
                  <l>Milke, that in blood runs out as faſt againe,</l>
                  <l>While the affrighted mother, with her hands</l>
                  <l>Heau'd vp, like <hi>Niobe,</hi> turn'd Marble, ſtands.</l>
                  <l>In euery place that doth afford an age</l>
                  <l>Markt out for ſlaughter, death and fury rage,</l>
                  <l>While y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore ſoules, ſome for their mothers crying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some ſmiling on their murderers, are dying.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O here a while your ſpeedy haſte forbeare</l>
                  <l>Compaſſionate parents, and vouchſafe a teare!</l>
                  <l>Thinke but what ſad, what ſoule affrighting ſight</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſaw, when they were rob'd of their delight.</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe your Infants whom you highly prize,</l>
                  <l>Snatcht from your armes, and ſlaine before your eyes,</l>
                  <l>What would you doe in ſuch a caſe as this?</l>
                  <l>Nay, what would you not doe? ſurely amiſſe</l>
                  <l>I doe conceiue, or elſe your ſorrow would</l>
                  <l>Be greater farre, then all their ſuffering could;</l>
                  <l>While from their pretty eyes ſalt teares did trill,</l>
                  <l>Your pierced hearts would liquid blood diſtill;</l>
                  <l>And euery wound their bodies ſhould receiue</l>
                  <l>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> murderers hands, your very ſoules would cleaue.</l>
                  <l>And yet behold ſuch was the wofull ſtate</l>
                  <l>Of that late happy Citie, fortunate</l>
                  <l>Erſt in her Sauiour, who there firſt drew breath,</l>
                  <l>But now moſt wretched in her childrens death,</l>
                  <l>Whileſt by this fearefull act of ſinne and ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Of Bethlehem a Bethauen it became.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But not this bloody act could yet aſſwage</l>
                  <l>Either their cruelty, or <hi>Herods</hi> rage,</l>
                  <l>No, the neare Villages in her hard fate</l>
                  <l>The wofull City muſt aſſociate:</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:19248:35"/>
                  <l>Not one poore cottage can keepe out pale death,</l>
                  <l>Wherein a child ſucks in an infant breath.</l>
                  <l>They paſſe through all the coaſts about, and ſtriue,</l>
                  <l>That not one Infant may be left aliue:</l>
                  <l>Their charge ſo ready are they to fulfill,</l>
                  <l>And ſatisfie the Tyrant in his will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O mercileſſe and matchleſſe murderers.</l>
                  <l>How can you thinke wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n iuſtice once preferres</l>
                  <l>A bill againſt your liues, and death you brings</l>
                  <l>Fore the Tribunall of the King of Kings</l>
                  <l>To anſwer this foule act? when their blood cries</l>
                  <l>To Heauen for vengeance, it will not ſuffice</l>
                  <l>That you had <hi>Herods</hi> Warrant, Gods Command</l>
                  <l>Did you knew well 'gainſt murder firmely ſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But how haue I forgot you all this while,</l>
                  <l>Poore Innocents, delay muſt not beguile</l>
                  <l>You of your worthy ſuffering, ample glory,</l>
                  <l>The which alone deſerues to make a ſtory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Church on blood, and the not doing wrong,</l>
                  <l>But ſuffering for it, hath foundation ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>By perſecution ſhe receiues renowne,</l>
                  <l>And martyrdome giues her a glorious Crowne.</l>
                  <l>The blood of <hi>Abel</hi> at the Worlds creation</l>
                  <l>Of this truth giues a pregnant demonſtration:</l>
                  <l>So lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wiſe in the Goſpels pupi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lage,</l>
                  <l>The blood of Infants, ſlaine by <hi>Herods</hi> rage.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There be two colours which God much delight,</l>
                  <l>And they are white and red: firſt, the pure white</l>
                  <l>Of innocence, then martyrdomes blood red,</l>
                  <l>And b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th theſe in the Infants largely ſpread:</l>
                  <l>Not all the coates, though quartered nere ſo faire,</l>
                  <l>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re men th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir armes emblazon, to repaire</l>
                  <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>try of their Family,</l>
                  <l>Which time would weare out but for Heraldry,</l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:19248:35"/>
                  <l>Are halfe ſo glorious, as thoſe faire Armes were,</l>
                  <l>Theſe Innocents did in their Scutcheon beare,</l>
                  <l>For, croſſe of Gules in Argent field they carry,<note place="margin">Verſus eſt vagitus in ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dium luctus in iubilum. Cyprian. O paruuli beati nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum lucta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Well may their Creſt be a rich Crowne of glory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some doubt, but ſuch either doe iudgement want,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe of charitie are wondrous ſcant,</l>
                  <l>Whether theſe Infants here depriu'd of breath,</l>
                  <l>Were ſau'd or no from an eternall death:</l>
                  <l>But what ſhould this ſtrange dubitation breed?</l>
                  <l>Is not Gods promiſe made vnto the ſeed</l>
                  <l>Of faithfull parents? Were not theſe receiu'd</l>
                  <l>Into the couenant ere of life bereau'd?</l>
                  <l>They were, they were, therefore their cry did turne</l>
                  <l>To ioy, and they now laugh, who then did mourne:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O bleſſed Infants, whom the cunning Diuell</l>
                  <l>By his temptation neuer led to euill,</l>
                  <l>With death you ſtruggled hard, and for that ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>You are now crowned with immortall life.</l>
                  <l>Sure <hi>Herods</hi> flattery could nere haue wrought you</l>
                  <l>So great a bleſſing as his fury brought you.</l>
                  <l>O bleſſed age, which could not ſpeake Chriſts Name,</l>
                  <l>Yet was thought worthy to die for the ſame:</l>
                  <l>Sure you were borne in a thrice happy time,</l>
                  <l>Felicities high toy ſo ſoone to clime.</l>
                  <l>You are ſcarce paſt the threſhold of your birth,</l>
                  <l>When life comes forth to meet you, and from earth</l>
                  <l>Takes you to heauen; you doe no ſooner leaue</l>
                  <l>Your infant cradles, but a Throne receiue:</l>
                  <l>In ſtead of hanging at your mothers breaſt</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome you ſecurely reſt:</l>
                  <l>Faire Infants whom the ancient Church did hold</l>
                  <l>The Flowers of Martyrs, ſprung vp in the cold</l>
                  <l>Of vnbeliefe, whoſe buds were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pt to death,<note place="margin">Flores mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrum. Aug.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>By froſt like perſecutions bitter breath,</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:19248:36"/>
                  <l>O how your death due prayſe to Chriſt affords,<note place="margin">Sanguine non lingua paſſione non Sermone. Chryſoſt.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>By blood, not tongue; in wounds, and not in words.</l>
                  <l>When greedy Wolfe the Lambe doth beare away,</l>
                  <l>The tender fleſh torne by his teeth, ſome ſay,</l>
                  <l>In taſte, if eaten, men ſhall ſweeter finde,</l>
                  <l>Then others killed whole of the ſame kind:</l>
                  <l>This obſeruation whether true or no,</l>
                  <l>Is not materiall any way to know:</l>
                  <l>Certaine it is, the fleſh of theſe brought vnder</l>
                  <l>The fangs of woluiſh <hi>Herod,</hi> torne aſunder,</l>
                  <l>Was ſweet vnto the Lord, and gaue delight:</l>
                  <l>For death of Saints is pretious in his ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That children ſhould teach men, may ſeeme 'gainſt ſence,</l>
                  <l>Yet we may learne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, faire innocence</l>
                  <l>In all our ſufferings muſt companion be:</l>
                  <l>For if we ſuffer ought deſeruedly,</l>
                  <l>With theſe we can expect no Crowne to take;</l>
                  <l>The cauſe, not croſſe, doth a true mart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r make:<note place="margin">Cauſa non poenafacit Martyrem. Auguſt.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>If that be good, though <hi>Herods</hi> doe conſpire</l>
                  <l>Againſt our liues, and threaten ſword or fire,</l>
                  <l>They may our bodies, not our ſoules diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>And their hate ſhall but worke our happineſſe,</l>
                  <l>Our croſſe ſhall crowne vs, and the death they giue,</l>
                  <l>Shall be a meanes to make vs euer liue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now was fulfill'd that fatall Prophecy,</l>
                  <l>Which was foretold of yore by <hi>Jeremy;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 30. 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>A voice was heard in Rama, whoſe dire ſound</l>
                  <l>In woe and lamentation did abound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Among thoſe mothers which were childleſſe made,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rachel</hi> was one, whom griefe did ſo inuade,</l>
                  <l>That ſhunning company, ſhe ſeem'd to liue,</l>
                  <l>As ſhe were borne for nothing but to grieue.</l>
                  <l>A ſhady Groue neare her now hated-home</l>
                  <l>A neighbour ſtood, there did ſhe often rome</l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:19248:36"/>
                  <l>In that thicke Couert, which made day like night,</l>
                  <l>She ſought to hide her from all humane ſight:</l>
                  <l>Sometime ſhe ſets her downe cloſe by the foote</l>
                  <l>Of a faire ſpreading tree, vpon whoſe roote</l>
                  <l>With nimble hand ſhe 'gins to carue her woes,</l>
                  <l>But ere ſhe halfe haue done, her paſſion growes</l>
                  <l>To ſuch a height, ſhe marres what ſhe hath made;</l>
                  <l>Then with ſterne rage the barke ſhe doth inuade,</l>
                  <l>Stabbing, and mangling of it without ſtint,</l>
                  <l>As if her Infants wounds ſhe there could print.</l>
                  <l>Starting at this, as if feare wings did borrow,</l>
                  <l>She fled, as if ſhe would out-run her ſorrow:</l>
                  <l>At laſt a burbling Brooke ſhe doth eſpie,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe noiſe, ſhe thought, did hold fit ſympathy</l>
                  <l>With her in mourning, there ſhe ſtayes her pace,</l>
                  <l>And ſeated neare it, doth extend her face</l>
                  <l>Ouer the current: hauing fixt her looke</l>
                  <l>A while vpon the Streame, ſhe chides the Brooke</l>
                  <l>For his to ſpeedy paſſage: Stay, O ſtay</l>
                  <l>Thy courſe, relentleſſe Torrent, did ſhe ſay,</l>
                  <l>And carry my complaints with thee along,</l>
                  <l>My words, although my woes, ſhall not be long:</l>
                  <l>Say that a Mother of two hopefull twinnes</l>
                  <l>Rob'd of that ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leſſe iſſue, for her ſinnes,</l>
                  <l>Will neuer ceaſe to mourne their bloody death,</l>
                  <l>Till the iuſt heauens in pitty ſtop her breath;</l>
                  <l>And for this kindneſſe, I to thee will pay</l>
                  <l>My teares, as a due tribute euery day.</l>
                  <l>This ſaid, her eyes a liquid ſhewre diſtill,</l>
                  <l>As they the Fountaine were, the Streame to fill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All that was done, which ſhe thought vndeſcried,</l>
                  <l>By a neere Kinſman of hers was eſpied,</l>
                  <l>Who now approacht, and ſitting downe beſide her,</l>
                  <l>In this milde manner did begin to chide her.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:19248:37"/>
                  <l>For ſhame at laſt leaue to be thus alone,</l>
                  <l>And vnto ſenceleſſe things to vent your mone;</l>
                  <l>Your faith and patience I once thought more ſtrong:</l>
                  <l>Griefes that recureleſſe are ſhould not be long:</l>
                  <l>By your immoderate ſorrow you offend</l>
                  <l>The higheſt Powers, and haſten on your end.</l>
                  <l>Beſide ſuch griefe is vaine, whether the dead,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe the liuing be conſidered:</l>
                  <l>The firſt, if they die well, are bleſt; if faile</l>
                  <l>Of a good end, our teares will nought auaile:</l>
                  <l>Your Infants death in innocency found,</l>
                  <l>This ſhould you rather comfort, then confound.</l>
                  <l>The body the ſoules priſon's ſaid to be,</l>
                  <l>Now it is death which ſets this priſoner free,</l>
                  <l>Who mournes for the enlargement of his child?</l>
                  <l>But 'tis the bodies death that makes you wild.</l>
                  <l>If it be ſo, O be no longer ſory,</l>
                  <l>That falls to riſe againe in greater glory.</l>
                  <l>Who grieues to ſee a houſe puld to the ground,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall he knowes be better built? Some bound</l>
                  <l>Set to your ſorrow then, God will reſtore</l>
                  <l>The body farre more glorious then before.</l>
                  <l>Looke on your ſelfe, and you will find it vaine,</l>
                  <l>So great a griefe ſo long to entertaine:</l>
                  <l>For ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> your teares in as great plenty fall.</l>
                  <l>As blood did from your Infants, could they call</l>
                  <l>Your children backe to life, no, though you mourne,</l>
                  <l>And pine to nothing, they ſhall nere returne.</l>
                  <l>Take comfort then, leſt if you ſorrow ſtill,</l>
                  <l>You ſeeme to ſpurne againſt <hi>Iehouahs</hi> will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ued Mother, who had all this while</l>
                  <l>In much impatience heard him, with a ſmile</l>
                  <l>Borrowed from ſcorne, thus anſwered, that they liue</l>
                  <l>In health can eaſily good counſell giue</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:19248:37"/>
                  <l>To ſuch as languiſh in diſeaſe and paine,</l>
                  <l>And they as hardly doe it entertaine:</l>
                  <l>Words are but words, I neuer yet could heare,</l>
                  <l>That the grieu'd heart was cured by the eare.</l>
                  <l>Aſwell may he which hath deſire to eate,</l>
                  <l>Be ſatisfied by ſeeing painted meat:</l>
                  <l>Or he that is through cold like to expire,</l>
                  <l>Warme his numbe limbes at the Apes Gloworme fire:</l>
                  <l>As I from cold and painted comfort finde</l>
                  <l>A medicine, to recure my thought ſicke minde,</l>
                  <l>Withall that I can from poore patience borrow,</l>
                  <l>I cannot pay ſo great a debt of ſorrow:</l>
                  <l>In vaine you waſte your words, my woes are more</l>
                  <l>Then time can weare away; therefore giue ore</l>
                  <l>Your fruitleſſe counſell, ſince my children are not,</l>
                  <l>Though I conſume my ſelfe in griefe, I care not;</l>
                  <l>Sorrow hath tane poſſeſſion in my breſt,</l>
                  <l>And onely can by death be diſpoſſeſt.</l>
                  <l>When ſhe had ſpoken thus, in haſty mood</l>
                  <l>She runnes, and hides her in the thickeſt Wood:</l>
                  <l>But while to trees ſhe doth her woes rehearſe,</l>
                  <l>To other matters I muſt turne my Verſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="Saturday" type="daily_meditation">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:19248:38"/>
               <head>Saturdaies Meditation, or the ſeuenth <hi>Canto.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>An Angell doth to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> tell</l>
                     <l>The death of <hi>Herod:</hi> Iſrael</l>
                     <l>He longs to viſit once againe:</l>
                     <l>Nazareth doth him entertaine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw was the time that the Lord meant to take</l>
                  <l>Vengeance on <hi>Herod,</hi> therefore he did make</l>
                  <l>By iuſt permiſſion, his owne iſſue ſtriue</l>
                  <l>How he might him of Crowne and life depriue:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod,</hi> while theſe foule treaſons were a breeding,</l>
                  <l>Got notice of <hi>Antipaters</hi> proceeding,</l>
                  <l>So was his baſe ſonne call'd: the yrkeſome thought</l>
                  <l>Of this vnnaturall action, quickly brought</l>
                  <l>Sickneſſe of minde vpon him: and that ſoare</l>
                  <l>Encreaſing, God did yet afflict him more,</l>
                  <l>And on his body lay a foule diſeaſe:</l>
                  <l>A ſecret fire he had, whoſe heate appeaſe</l>
                  <l>No courſe of Phyſicke could though much he tride,<note place="margin">Ioſep. de Bello Iud. lib. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>All was in vaine, the flame did quenchleſſe bide,</l>
                  <l>His bowels full of paine did not within,</l>
                  <l>And wormes to ſwarme about him did begin;</l>
                  <l>The Crampe and Dropſie on his limbs did ceaze,</l>
                  <l>And there was nothing which might giue him eaſe.</l>
                  <l>Paſſing o're Iordan, neere Aſphaltis Lake,</l>
                  <l>Calyrroes hot Bathes, he needes would make</l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:19248:38"/>
                  <l>A meanes vnto his cure, there he did baine,<note place="margin">Euſeb.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet as he went in, came out full of paine.</l>
                  <l>While <hi>Herod</hi> thus did in his torments broile,</l>
                  <l>Phiſicians gaue aduice, that in hot oile</l>
                  <l>His body ſhould be ſuppled, they prepare</l>
                  <l>A veſſell for that purpoſe, and with care</l>
                  <l>Put him therein; the fume perturbs his head</l>
                  <l>So much, that he is taken out halfe dead.</l>
                  <l>At laſt come to himſelfe, he knowes to ſure,</l>
                  <l>That he this euill ſeekes in vaine to cure.</l>
                  <l>Full of deſpaire, ſomewhat before his end,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Salome</hi> his ſiſter he doth ſend,</l>
                  <l>(Together with her husband <hi>Alexander</hi>)</l>
                  <l>And to performe this foule deſigne command her:</l>
                  <l>Siſter, you ſee (ſaid the ſicke man), that fate</l>
                  <l>Hath markt me out for death: the deadly hate</l>
                  <l>My ſubiects beare me, will not let them mourne</l>
                  <l>To ſee mine aſhes clos'd vp in their vrne:</l>
                  <l>The meaneſt of them will ſcarce daigne let fall</l>
                  <l>A teare, to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>our my ſad funerall,</l>
                  <l>Rather I feare they will exceed in mirth,</l>
                  <l>To ſee my body turn'd into his earth:</l>
                  <l>But I haue laid a plot their ioyes to croſſe,</l>
                  <l>And make the mourne, not mine, but their own loſſe,</l>
                  <l>Their ioyfull exclamations Ile ſtrike mute,</l>
                  <l>If you but faithfull be to execute:</l>
                  <l>All their young Nobles (ſo haue I diſpos'd)</l>
                  <l>Within <hi>Hyppod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>omus</hi> are faſt enclos'd,</l>
                  <l>And a ſtrong guard about it, at my death,</l>
                  <l>Aſſoone as euer you ſhall ſee my br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ath</l>
                  <l>Forſake my body, giue a ſtrict command,</l>
                  <l>That they may all be murder'd out of hand;</l>
                  <l>So when my corps vnto the graue ſhall goe,</l>
                  <l>The Iewes ſhall mourne whether they will or no:</l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:19248:39"/>
                  <l>So ſhall I haue a glorious Epitaph,</l>
                  <l>And though low vnder ground, ſhall highly laugh.</l>
                  <l>This ſaid, his ill increaſing more and more,</l>
                  <l>And his deſpaire growne greater then before,</l>
                  <l>Taking an Apple (ſuch was then his meate)</l>
                  <l>And being wont to pare, and ſo to eate,</l>
                  <l>In haſty wiſe he called for a kntfe,</l>
                  <l>And with that ſought to rid himſelfe of life:</l>
                  <l>But either his weake arme this foule intent</l>
                  <l>Could not performe, or others did preuent</l>
                  <l>The fatall blow: and muſt I then ſtill liue?</l>
                  <l>Cryed out the Tyrant? Will the iuſt Heauens giue</l>
                  <l>No end vnto my ſufferings? Muſt I be</l>
                  <l>The Ball of ſcorne, and Butt of miſery?</l>
                  <l>Breake breake my heart! flie forth impriſon'd breath!</l>
                  <l>And welcome, what I haue long lookt for, death.</l>
                  <l>More he had ſaid, but that he ſcarce had ſpoke</l>
                  <l>This, when with rage his very heart ſtrings broke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>While <hi>Herod</hi> thus in horror breath'd his laſt,</l>
                  <l>A bleſſed Angell doth to Egypt haſt,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Ioſeph</hi> may haue word of this euent,</l>
                  <l>Which well he knew would giue no ſmall content</l>
                  <l>To him, ſo long an exile: in the night,</l>
                  <l>When dreames the fancy pleaſe, or elſe affright,</l>
                  <l>The Angell makes approach, and thus begins:</l>
                  <l>The Tyrant <hi>Herod,</hi> whoſe abhorred ſinnes</l>
                  <l>Did crie ſo long for vengeance vnto Heauen,</l>
                  <l>At laſt is iuſtly of his life bereauen:</l>
                  <l>They that delight in blood not long endure,</l>
                  <l>Though God be ſlow in ſtriking, he ſtrikes ſure;</l>
                  <l>His hands be iron, though his feet be wooll,</l>
                  <l>And Tyrants neuer leaue, vntill they pull</l>
                  <l>Dire vengeance on their heads, which long delaid,</l>
                  <l>Falls with the heauier waight. Be not afraid</l>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:19248:39"/>
                  <l>Of any future miſchiefe, he that ſought</l>
                  <l>The Infants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath his owne deſtruction wrought:</l>
                  <l>Dead is the Wolfe, whoſe rage like fire did burne,</l>
                  <l>Backe to his paſture may the Lambe returne:</l>
                  <l>Therefore ariſe and take the bleſſed Childe,</l>
                  <l>Nor let thy care forget the Mother milde,</l>
                  <l>To Iſrael with them returne againe,</l>
                  <l>In Egypt thou no longer maiſt remaine.</l>
                  <l>This meſſage which the Lord did now direct</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Joſeph,</hi> ſhewes that he doth his reſpect:</l>
                  <l>Gods Saints in trouble muſt not alwaies liue,</l>
                  <l>In time he will a ioyfull iſſue giue</l>
                  <l>To all their ſorrowes: <hi>Ioſeph</hi> may be caſt</l>
                  <l>Into a lothſome priſon, but at laſt</l>
                  <l>He ſhall come forth with honour: for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iob</hi> may in anguiſh on the dunghill ſit,</l>
                  <l>Scraping his ſoares, ere long a happier fate</l>
                  <l>Shall crowne his ioyes, and double his eſtate:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Daniel</hi> through enuie of malicious men</l>
                  <l>May cloſed be within the lyons denne,</l>
                  <l>But he their vtmoſt furie ſhall withſtand,</l>
                  <l>And after liue aduanced in the land:</l>
                  <l>Babylons king may giue command to throw</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſt <hi>Sadruc, Meſſhac,</hi> and <hi>Abednego.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Into the fornace, but he ſhall admire</l>
                  <l>To ſee them walke vnhurt, vntoucht by fire,</l>
                  <l>And afterward, their innocence to grace,</l>
                  <l>Ouer the Kingdome ſeat them in high place.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioſeph</hi> an exile may from <hi>Herod</hi> flie,</l>
                  <l>But in this perſecution muſt not die,</l>
                  <l>Now the time comes, when he by Gods command</l>
                  <l>Muſt trauai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e back to his owne natiue land,</l>
                  <l>And with a happy ſalutation greet,</l>
                  <l>His Galile, whoſe ſmoke he held ſo ſweet:</l>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:19248:40"/>
                  <l>Like as a man for ſome long tedious time</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>niſht from his deare Country, to a Clime</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arſh and vnpleaſant, will, if he doe heare</l>
                  <l>His baniſhment repeal'd, with greedy eare</l>
                  <l>Receiue the happy newes, and in his mind</l>
                  <l>A not to be expreſſed comfort find:</l>
                  <l>So fared it with our <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when he knew</l>
                  <l>The tidings of the Tyrants death were true,</l>
                  <l>And that he might returne to Iſrael,</l>
                  <l>From which in exile he ſo long did dwell,</l>
                  <l>With a glad heart, and more then common care,</l>
                  <l>He all things for his iourney doth prepare,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſcarce ſalutes the lightſome day,</l>
                  <l>When he b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gins his trauaile, by the way</l>
                  <l>Rendring due thankes to that Almighty power,</l>
                  <l>Which had preſeru'd him to this bleſſed hower.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Suppoſe by this time they are ſafe arriu'd</l>
                  <l>There, where vnwearied labour had ſo ſtriu'd</l>
                  <l>To bring them to the Land of Paleſtine,</l>
                  <l>Here <hi>Ioſeph</hi> doth enquire about the line</l>
                  <l>Of the deceaſed Tyrant, and being told</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Archelaus</hi> did the Scepter hold</l>
                  <l>After his father: ſuch mans weakeneſſe is,</l>
                  <l>Though hitherto the Lord did neuer miſſe</l>
                  <l>Safely to guard him a cold trembling feare</l>
                  <l>Paſſing the maze of his offended eare,</l>
                  <l>Tooke hold vpon his heart: the beſt of Saints</l>
                  <l>While here they liue, liue not without their taints.</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Lot,</hi> when Sodome was conſum'd with fire,</l>
                  <l>Did doubt the Mountaines ſafety, and deſire</l>
                  <l>A place of ſurer refuge: ſo the ſight</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Eſaus</hi> Band of men did much affright</l>
                  <l>Perplexed <hi>Iacob,</hi> when he did repaire</l>
                  <l>Backe to his natiue home: O can deſpaire</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19248:40"/>
                  <l>Lay hold on ſuch as theſe? what then ſhall we</l>
                  <l>Doe, when in danger and extremity?</l>
                  <l>So great a power hath feare vpon our ſoules,<note place="margin">Reseſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioſa ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor. Ouid. Saepius opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nione quam re la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Soneca.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>That it checks vertue, and euen grace controules,</l>
                  <l>And yet ſometimes (though feare ſo farre proceed,)</l>
                  <l>We ſuffer in opinion, not indeed.</l>
                  <l>But why, O <hi>Ioſeph</hi> wert thou thus afraid?</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou miſdoubt the Lord would ſend thee aid,</l>
                  <l>And propulſe danger from thee? Could thy mind</l>
                  <l>Conceiue a thought of feare? Since thou didſt find</l>
                  <l>Thy gracious God ſo ready ſtill to ſend</l>
                  <l>An Angell for thy guard? Did he defend</l>
                  <l>Thee and thy charge from <hi>Herods</hi> cruelty,</l>
                  <l>To let you fall by his ſonnes tyranny?</l>
                  <l>Was his arme ſhortned, or his loue growne leſſe,</l>
                  <l>That now he could not as much care expreſſe</l>
                  <l>In preſeruation of you, as before?</l>
                  <l>Ah no, Gods loue encreaſeth more and more</l>
                  <l>To ſuch as ſerue him, and his power extends</l>
                  <l>Beyond all limitation to his friends.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> grant thou mightſt, as not vnlikely gather,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Archelaus</hi> would be like his father,</l>
                  <l>A bloody Tyrant, for a wicked Sire<note place="margin">Mali coru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> malum ouum. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leaues his ſonne like himſelfe: a ſtrong deſire</l>
                  <l>To be thought apt for imitation,</l>
                  <l>Leades children to obſerue their parents faſhion:</l>
                  <l>But yet for all this thou maiſt reſt ſecure,</l>
                  <l>He who hath vndertaken, will procure</l>
                  <l>Safety for thee and thine, onely be bold,</l>
                  <l>And on his goodneſſe by true faith lay hold:</l>
                  <l>Danger may threaten, but it ſhall not harme</l>
                  <l>Such as are guarded by th'Almighties arme.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now was the time, that <hi>Morpheus</hi> with his wand</l>
                  <l>Did charme a ſilent ſleepe on all the Land,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19248:41"/>
                  <l>Only perplexed <hi>Ioſeph</hi> could not reſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>any cares lay tumbling in his breaſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he while he thought he ſhould moſt ſafety find</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> going back to Egypt: but his mind</l>
                  <l>Did quickly alter, when the Lords command</l>
                  <l>Which bad expreſſely he ſhould leaue the land</l>
                  <l>To his remembrance came: then he thought beſt</l>
                  <l>Where he now lodged to ſet vp his reſt:</l>
                  <l>But that was daſht, when being come ſo neare</l>
                  <l>He did conſider an vnmanly feare</l>
                  <l>Should keepe him from his home: in maze of doubt</l>
                  <l>An Angell came at laſt to lead him out,</l>
                  <l>Giuing direction, he ſhould not abide</l>
                  <l>Neare <hi>Archelaus</hi> eye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but turne aſide</l>
                  <l>Into the parts of Galile, for there</l>
                  <l>He might ſecurely liue, without all feare</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioſeph</hi> obeyes and now his courſe he bends</l>
                  <l>To Nazareth, where all his trauaile ends:</l>
                  <l>Forfully ſeated there he liues in peace</l>
                  <l>With his ſoules comfort, and his ioyes encreaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And this ſaith the Euangeliſt was done,</l>
                  <l>That there might be a conſummation</l>
                  <l>Of what the Prophets told of Chriſt: for he</l>
                  <l>A Nazarite ſay they ſhall called be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Expoſitors haue here been much perplext,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they can directly find this text</l>
                  <l>In none of all the Prophets; ſome conceaue</l>
                  <l>That time which doth of many things bereaue</l>
                  <l>The world, hath in his reuolution loſt</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſacred books, where theſe things were engro'ſt<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Another before this his ſence preferres.</l>
                  <l>And doth for Prophets read int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rs,<note place="margin">Iſidor.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>For Prophets may be thought to ſay that thing,</l>
                  <l>Which men from them by good deduction bring.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19248:41"/>
                  <l>But matter fetcht ſo farre wee need not vſe,</l>
                  <l>Or ſeeke the ſacred writer to excuſe:</l>
                  <l>For holy writ two waies a thing affords,</l>
                  <l>Either according to the ſence or words:</l>
                  <l>Now though we meet not the ſame words in ſound,</l>
                  <l>Yet the ſame ſence in Scripture may be found.</l>
                  <l>Nazaren ſignifies one flouriſhing,</l>
                  <l>And doth not <hi>Eſay</hi> call this heauenly King</l>
                  <l>A Rod of <hi>Ieſſes</hi> Stem, a branch that growes</l>
                  <l>Out of his roote, each one that Scripture knowes,<note place="margin">Iſal. 11. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Knowes this prophetique truth: Againe this name</l>
                  <l>Is giuen him, that he may haue the ſame</l>
                  <l>Which his type had before him: Sampſons facts</l>
                  <l>Did but foreſignifie our Sauiours acts:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sampſon</hi> from barraine parents did proceed:</l>
                  <l>And Chriſt alone was the pure Virgins ſeed:</l>
                  <l>His killing of the lyon did foretell</l>
                  <l>Chriſt ſhould that roaring lyons power quell:</l>
                  <l>Slaughtering his foes euen when he loſt his breath</l>
                  <l>ſhewed Chriſt ſhould ouercome his foes by death:</l>
                  <l>Now of the firſt we read that he was ſtil'd</l>
                  <l>A Nazarite to God: therefore this child<note place="margin">Iudg. 13. 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>That truth and type might fitly both agree,</l>
                  <l>was call'd a Nazaren as well as he.</l>
                  <l>But properly his name came from the place</l>
                  <l>Hight Nazareth, which had the happy grace</l>
                  <l>To giue him education as a bower</l>
                  <l>Moſt fit to entertaine ſo ſweet a flower.</l>
                  <l>Nazareth doth a flower ſignifie,</l>
                  <l>And what place could he better dignifie</l>
                  <l>With his abode, then that whoſe name expreſt</l>
                  <l>His nature, who of all flowers was the beſt:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alcinous</hi> garden, or <hi>Adonis</hi> Bower,</l>
                  <l>Was neuer deckt with halfe ſo rare a flower,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19248:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Thoſe of the greateſt beauty are but ſilly</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Sharons Roſe, or to the Valleys Lilly.</l>
                  <l>This is not like French Flowers, in out ſide braue,</l>
                  <l>Which yet within nor ſent, nor vertue haue,</l>
                  <l>No, from an outſide meane there doth diſtill</l>
                  <l>Such vertue, as the Saints with grace doth fill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Soule a Noſegay is, if this adorne it,</l>
                  <l>The Lord will take the ſent, if not, hee'l ſcorne it.</l>
                  <l>O may this bleſſed flower which now doth grow</l>
                  <l>In Heauens high Nazareth, not here below,</l>
                  <l>Make vs ſo ſweetly in Gods noſtrils ſmell,</l>
                  <l>That we tranſplanted from the earth may dwell</l>
                  <l>In Heauen for euer, and in ſuch a ioy,</l>
                  <l>As time cannot weare out, or death deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>Flouriſh with Chriſt, and blisfull Peans ſing,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the praiſe of our eternall King.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 3. l. 2. r. <hi>an.</hi> l 25. r. <hi>armies.</hi> p. 10. l. 10. r. <hi>Iew.</hi> l 27. r. <hi>ſucceſſors.</hi> p. 13. l. 2. r <hi>y'runne.</hi> p. 16 l. 25. r. <hi>thy.</hi> p. 17 l 17. r. <hi>when</hi> p. 18. l. 6. r. <hi>humane.</hi> p. 19. l. 20. r. <hi>leeſe.</hi> p. 31. l 18. r. <hi>nonce.</hi> p. 34. l. 10. r. <hi>repurchace.</hi> p. 43 l. 16. r. <hi>Ewe.</hi> p. 45. l. 14. r <hi>yeld.</hi> p. 49. l. 19. r. <hi>kill.</hi> p. 57. l. 22. r <hi>in.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19248:42"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
